<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters of love and gallantry, and several other subjects. Vol. II written by ladies ; with a dialogue between love and reason, shewing, the reasonableness and unreasonableness of love, the nun's letter to the monk, characters and pictures of several ladies and gentlemen, with other passionate letters that passed betwixt both sexes, in town and country.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48256</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12185312</idno>
  <idno type="VID">55740</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240953921</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2117</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12185312</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55740)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 605:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Letters of love and gallantry, and several other subjects. Vol. II written by ladies ; with a dialogue between love and reason, shewing, the reasonableness and unreasonableness of love, the nun's letter to the monk, characters and pictures of several ladies and gentlemen, with other passionate letters that passed betwixt both sexes, in town and country.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 177, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for S. Briscoe ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: prelim. p. [1] and p. [1]-[3] at end.</note>
                  <note>"Advertisement. Letters of love and gallantry, and several other subjects, all written by ladies : with the memoirs, life and adventures of a young lady; written by herself. Vol. I": prelim. p. [1].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Love --  Literary collections.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:55740:1"/>
            <head>Advertisement.</head>
            <p>LEtters of <hi>Love and Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry,</hi> and several other Subjects; All written by Ladies: With the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs, Life and Adventures of a young Lady; written by her Self.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VOL. I.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55740:1"/>
            <p>LETTERS OF <hi>Love and Gallantry.</hi> And several other Subjects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by Ladies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VOL. II.</p>
            <p>With a DIALOGUE between LOVE and REASON: <hi>SHEWING,</hi> The Reasonableness and Unreasonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of <hi>LOVE;</hi> The Nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Letter to the Monk; Characters and Pictures of several Ladies and Gentlemen; with other Passionate Letters, that passed betwixt both Sexes, in Town and Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dedicated to the</hi> Beaux.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Charles-street</hi> in <hi>Russel-street, Covent-Garden,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:55740:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55740:2"/>
            <head>THE Epistle Dedicatory TO THE BEAUX.</head>
            <p>SInce we are satisfied of your Friendly readiness to Publish our Favours, even before you have receiv'd 'em, we thought our selves oblig'd
<pb facs="tcp:55740:3"/> by so much good nature, to give you once a just occasion for't, and present you with our Letters. Some fill their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications with nothing but Apologys for their making 'em: Some cunningly place the name at the bottom of the Picture, to try if our Wit could guess at what they meant by the Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing above: Others, as 'twere on design, write you asleep in the beginning, to convince you they're in Love, as they tell you, at the latter end: while this Geographically Witty ever treats you with a Fool of such or such a Climate, and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels
<pb facs="tcp:55740:3"/> for business to <hi>Japan,</hi> or <hi>Arragon,</hi> when God knows, and you may convince him, we have as much, as he can turn his hand to, at Home: Nay, some, tho' they were Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressing to you, would have the impertinence to bring in Latin and Greek. Thus all, like true Lovers, talk least of the thing they come about: but we, skill'd in Men, are too sensible how pleasing 'tis to know we are admir'd, to entertain you with any thing but your selves; and shall clear our selves from the Sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion of Flattery in such
<pb facs="tcp:55740:4"/> Cases, when you know our Complement to you is an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of a Quarrel that lately happen'd among us about you; and sure you can't believe we flatter, when it comes to that: To make short, meeting the other Day at— after the usual Entertainment of Modes and Dressing, we na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally fell into Discourse of you; when each singled out her Man, and strove to set him uppermost; one was prais'd for his way of Dress, another for the throw of his Periwig, this for a pretty Face, and and that for the Airy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement
<pb facs="tcp:55740:4"/> of an ugly one: the Dispute was hotly maintain'd a great while, but finding no end could be made in this, because there was thought to be no Standard for Beauty; we unanimonsly resolv'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the business by their Writing: Much was said on all hands, and many shrewd Criticisms made: This Man's Verses were arraign'd for Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence; and that many Plays for having in 'em more Bawdy than Wit.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55740:5"/>
            <p>Another's Songs were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd for having nothing in 'em; but because 'twas uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal with such Writers, the Remark was not taken notice of; She that accus'd 'em growing angry that She could not come in for her Share of abusing, fell foul on the Author's Person, and said that he mov'd by the same Rules that he Writ, that every thing was so stiff about him, that nothing was out of Form, and that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Form, that he minc'd all his Words, to make 'em come fine from him:
<pb facs="tcp:55740:5"/> and to make us the better understand her the other day, said She, when a common Man would have said, <hi>'Twas a rude thing,</hi> turning to me, his Face and Body in one Motion, <hi>Madam,</hi> said he, <hi>I protest 'twas most dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingagingly done:</hi> Was there ever such an Ape? Nay, tho' he be the most ugly of them all, yet in his Songs is ever dying for Love. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, She that admir'd him, cou'd hold no longer, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd to revenge the abuse of his Person and Parts on her Head-dress; the rest of
<pb facs="tcp:55740:6"/> us thought our Cause as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Defending, and each drew out against her, that had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd it, when <hi>C</hi>—coming in, put a stop to the War.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55740:6"/>
            <head>MEMOIRS OF THE Fair <hi>Eloisa,</hi> a NUN, AND <hi>Abelard</hi> a MONK.</head>
            <p>IN Order the better to understand all the Beauties of the following Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is necessary to know the Characters of <hi>Eloisa</hi> and <hi>Abelard,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so what sort of Commerce they held to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and consequently to give an Abridgement of both their Lives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abelard</hi> liv'd in the Year 1170. under the Reign of <hi>Lewis the Young,</hi> and was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55740:7"/> very famous for his Wit and Gallantry. He is reported to be the Inventor of Scholastick Philosophy, which is a very difficult Amusement. Others say, that he was also the Author of the Romance of the <hi>Rose,</hi> a very agreeable description of Love. The said Romance being in Vogue to this very day, and the said Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy still profess'd, might suffice to give us a very great and Noble <hi>Idea</hi> of him. But besides that, he has shown in most of his Works, and in the whole Conduct of his Life, a surprising clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Mind, an Universal Capacity, a greatness of Soul which nothing could overcome, much delicacy in the Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and a great deal of firmness in his Misfortunes: In fine, that which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses the best and most Excellent part of the merit of great Men, is the true Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of <hi>Abelard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eloisa</hi> was a Gentlewoman of a very good Family, about Eighteen Years of Age, very Witty and Sprightly, who had Beauty enough to move the most In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensible: Her Parents being very Rich, resolv'd to add an extraordinary Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to those Natural Endowments. An Uncle of hers, who was Canon of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55740:7"/> Church of <hi>Paris,</hi> apply'd himself most carefully about it; and as he Lov'd her intirely, he spar'd neither cost nor care to effect it; and prov'd so successful therein, that the World was fill'd with the Praise of his Niece's Beauty and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishments.</p>
            <p>Such Admirable Qualifications soon Captivated the Inclinations of all those that knew her. <hi>Abelard</hi> was one of the first that felt the Power of her Charms, and became passionately in Love with her. His Philosophy was not capable to defend his Heart against those Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he has describ'd himself under the Name of <hi>Beauty</hi> in his Romance of the <hi>Rose;</hi> neither did he in the least en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to contend with his Passion. On the contrary, being wholly taken up with his Love, he abandon'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self intirely to it, and only study'd how to declare it to the Person he Ador'd. He being very well shap'd, Young, and having a high Reputation in the World, did not question but his Declaration would meet with all the Success he could expect, he tells us himself, <hi>Tanti quippe tunc neminis eram, &amp; juventutis &amp; formae praeeminebam, ut quamcunque feminarum
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55740:8"/> nostro dignarer amore, nullam vererer repulsam▪</hi> That whatever Woman he could hav<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> fallen in Love with at that time, he ha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> reason to hope for every thing, and t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> undertake all, without the least fear of<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Refusal.</p>
            <p>Being thus confident of success, h<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> only long'd for an opportunity to mak<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> his Addresses to that Lovely Maid. H<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> flatter'd himself, that if he could once b<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> introduc'd into her Uncle's House, b<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> some of his Friends, he would soon ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tain the end of all his Wishes. He ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ply'd himself immediately about it; an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Friends he made use of, easily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd what he desir'd of <hi>Fulbert,</hi> (tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> was <hi>Eloisa</hi>'s Uncle's Name) who wa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> extreamly Covetous, and yet desir'd no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing so much as the advancement o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> his Niece, by reason that he could no possibly give her a better Master, or on<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that was less self-interested than <hi>Abelard</hi> Therefore he receiv'd him joyfully int<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> his House, and committed <hi>Eloisa</hi> to hi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Tuition and Care, desiring him, as<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> he had design'd to serve him in his Love to take an absolute Empire over hi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Niece, and to allow towards her Educa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion all the time he could spare from th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55740:8"/> Publick, to be with her Day and Night, to have a continual Eye upon her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and even to make use of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority he gave him, whenever he should find her remiss, or disobedient. <hi>Fulbert</hi> show'd a simplicity without Example in all this; since that by confiding thus in young People, and furnishing them him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, with a thousand Opportunities; it was almost impossible for them not to fall in Love with one another. But the Uncle's affection towards the Niece was so strong and so blind; and <hi>Abelard</hi>'s Reputation was so well establish'd throughout the Kingdom, that not har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring the least suspition of their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, he thought himself absolutely se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abelard,</hi> who easily promis'd whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Fulbert</hi> requir'd of him, did not fail to improve the liberty he had of seeing the Lovely <hi>Eloisa</hi> at all convenient hours, and Moments. He acquainted her with his Passion. and did it so well, that she hearken'd to it with pleasure. It is easie to persuade a Young Maid about Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen to Love; and <hi>Abelard</hi> was too Charming, and had too much Wit, not to make a considerable progress in her
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55740:9"/> Heart in a short time. She soon Lov'd him so tenderly that she could no longer refuse him any thing: Insomuch that being wholly taken up by a thousand Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal Caresses, in the injoyment of those Delights the Passion he had inspir'd her with afforded him, being continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with her, he often forgot his most se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and most Important Affairs. A Philosopher in Love, is no wiser than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Man; and however desirous to preserve his Reputation, he sooner or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter commits faults that are blam'd by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Body, though every Man would be guilty of the same.</p>
            <p>The World soon perceiv'd this Intrigue between the Master and the Schollar, so great an Assiduity in their Conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, together with the Tenderness and Passion that appear'd in all their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, soon discover'd that Philosophy was not always their Theme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fulbert</hi> was the only Person that had no Eyes to see what every Body else per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd; and whatever Advices he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd about it, he was so prepossessed with a good Opinion of <hi>Abelard</hi> and <hi>Eloisa</hi>'s Vertue, that it made no manner of impression upon him. Finally our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55740:9"/> Lovers keeping no measures in their Love, things went so far through their imprudence, that the Uncle, being at last undeceiv'd, resolv'd to part them, to prevent the ill consequences of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue. But it prov'd too late, for <hi>Eloisa</hi> soon discovering something extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary in her self, she acquainted <hi>Abelard</hi> therewith, who thereupon came back immediately to <hi>Paris,</hi> and stole her by Night, in order to Marry her privately, until her Relations would allow it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fulbert,</hi> who Lov'd <hi>Eloisa</hi> to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree that he could not live without her, was extreamly troubl'd at her Flight; and being moreover very sensible of the affront <hi>Abelard</hi> had put upon him in abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the Liberty he had given him, he was transported to that excess of Rage, that he swore to be reveng'd of him. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belard,</hi> who was conscious of the Guilt, and could not forbear looking upon his own behaviour, as a piece of Treachery, resolv'd to go back to <hi>Paris,</hi> in order to use his utmost Endeavours to appease <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi>'s Fury. To that end he made use of all the Entreaties, Submissions, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises he could think on. He begg'd of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55740:10"/> him above all things to reflect on the force of Love, and on the Faults that that Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of our Souls has often caus'd the greatest Men to commit. <hi>Fulbert</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembl'd his resentment, and pretended to be overcome by his Reasons, and to consent to all. He even Embrac'd him closely, the better to deceive him, and to secure his own Revenge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abelard</hi> being overjoy'd at <hi>Fulbert</hi>'s consent, went back to the place where he had left his Dear <hi>Eloisa,</hi> whom he Marry'd; but with so much Repugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on that fair one's part, that it prov'd a very difficult Task to perswade her. As her Sentiments were very nice, she could not indure the necessity she should be under of Loving him, nor the injury he was going to do himself by Marrying her. She could not indure to think he should be indebted to any thing for the Love she bore him, but to Love it self, and his Quality of Philosopher seem'd to her so inconsistent with the design of Marrying her, that she had rather a thousand times be look'd upon as his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress, than to become his Wife at the cost of his Reputation and Glory. And whereas <hi>Abelard</hi> had represented to her,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55740:10"/> that it would be the only way to appease <hi>Fulbert</hi>'s Anger, and to avoid the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge he meditated; she assur'd him that he flatter'd himself in vain, and that knowing her Uncle as well as she did, she could safely swear to him, that it was impossible to appease him, and that sooner or later he would endeavour to ruine him. However these Reasons not being able to perswade <hi>Abelard,</hi> she yielded to his Desires, only out of fear of displeasing him by her resistance. And it was not without Tears and Sighs that she consented to Marry a Man she Lov'd beyond expression, and by whom she was as tenderly belov'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eloisa</hi> was not deceiv'd in the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on she had of her Uncle. That Cruel Man still persevering in his design of Vengeance against <hi>Abelard,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing his Marriage with his Niece, found means to corrupt one of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to admit Russians into his Master's Chamber, who drawing near his Bed, while he was a asleep, at one stroke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the Man from the Lover. That Action was too black and too Tragical to remain unpunish'd. The Uncle's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state was Confiscated by a Decree from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55740:11"/> the Court; and one of the Assassinats to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Servant who had admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him were Condemn'd to lose their Eyes, and to suffer the same Punishment by the Hangman's Hand, which they had dared to attempt upon another. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter such a Misfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tune, our Philosopher in order to take such measures as were most suitable to the wretched Condition to which he was reduc'd, lock'd himself up in a Monastery, and caus'd <hi>Eloisa</hi> to retire into a Convent; and whither out of Jealousie, or Love; engag'd her to enter into Orders, before he had resolv'd to do the same himself.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, to keep up the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation he had acquir'd of being the most Learned Man of <hi>Europe,</hi> he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd the Acts of the Apostles to the Monks of the Abby of St. <hi>Dennis</hi> among whom he liv'd. And happening to have an occasion to speak of that Saint, he chanc'd to say, whither accidentally, or out of a Capricio, <hi>That</hi> Denis <hi>the</hi> Areo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagite <hi>never was in</hi> France. It is very well known, that to entertain any Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents in those Days contrary to that of the Monks, was sufficient to be reputed an Apostate or Heretick. Learning could
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55740:11"/> Authorize nothing, and those who soar'd a little above the common level, as soon as it was known were forc'd to condemn themselves to a voluntary Exile to avoid the publick Persecution of the Monks. St. <hi>Bernard</hi> was one of those that declar'd against <hi>Abelard,</hi> not for the same reason for which the Monks of St. <hi>Denis</hi> did it, but only because so much Wit, joyn'd to a worldly conduct seem'd dangerous to him. He concluded, That <hi>a Mans' Wit must needs be tainted, when the Heart was not pure-</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During this Storm; <hi>Abelard</hi> who real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly possess'd all the Qualifications that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose great Men, but yet was not so per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as to be a Saint; incens'd by so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Misfortunes and Injuries, resolv'd to sly from the Monks, and to retire into a Desart near <hi>Nogent.</hi> The Learned were scarce in that Age, and the desire of Learning began to spread. For that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son <hi>Abelard</hi> was sought after in his Exile; and being found out, was loaden with Presents by those who were desirous to hear his Lessons. Those Presents were so considerable as to enable him to build a House, and a Chappel, which he De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated under the Name of <hi>Paraclét,</hi> the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55740:12"/> first that ever had that Name in <hi>France:</hi> Which was represented by some as a Novelty which might have dangerous Consequences, though in reality it was only a Monument of the Consolations he had receiv'd from the Grace of God in that place, by a more serious appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to his Study, and a more absolute resignation of his Mistress. But Men of Merit, though never so retir'd are never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless expos'd to Envy. He was hardly well settl'd in his Solitude, when he was accus'd of Caballing. In order to justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie himself, he desir'd leave to quit it, and intreated the Archbishop of <hi>Troy,</hi> to permit him to settle some Maids there, and to assign his Chapel and his Estate to them. This Settlement being promis'd, he sent for <hi>Eloisa</hi> to Govern the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery, which having committed to her Care, he retir'd elsewhere. Happy if he had still been able to fly her.</p>
            <p>It was during that absence that a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he wrote to a Friend near <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naclét,</hi> in which he gave him a large ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Persecutions he had endur'd, sell accidentally into the hands of that new Abbess. She open'd it, and finding a thousand things in it, in which she was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55740:12"/> highly concern'd, she took an occasion from that to write the following Letter to him, to complain of his Conduct, and to ask him, Whither it was just for a Nice Lover to abandon her to the <hi>false Idea's</hi> which so long a silence might cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in her. <hi>That Letter</hi> (says he who has Collected the Works of <hi>Abelard) is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proper to show how far a Woman is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to carry the Sentiments of her Heart, when she joyns a Violent Passion to a good Education.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>Eloisa <hi>to</hi> Abelard. LETTER I.</head>
               <p>'TIS to her Master, and to her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; 'tis to her Brother, and to her Husband, that a Maid, a Daughter, a Sister, a Wife, and to include in one word, all that is Sublime, Respectful, Tender and free in those Names; 'tis to her <hi>Abelard Eloisa</hi> writes.</p>
               <p>A Letter of Consolation written by you to a Friend, lately fell into my hands, Knowing the Character, and being in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55740:13"/> Love with the Hand, my Heart joyning with my Curiosity, forc'd me to open it. To apologize for the Liberty I took, I flatter'd my self with the Sovereign Right I ought to have over all that comes from you, and I made a scruple to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there could be any Laws of Decorum I ought to observe when I had the means in my power to hear from you. But my Curiosity cost me very dear! What Anguish did it expose me to! And what could equal my Surprise when I found that Letter only contain'd a sad and long account of your Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes! I found my Name a hundred times in it: I never met with it without fear: Some Misfortune ever follow'd it. I also read yours in it which was no hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier. Those Fatal and Dear Idea's di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturb'd me to that degree, that I thought you did too much to comfort a Friend, to whom you did write about some In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerable Afflictions, in giving him a particular account of our Misfortunes and Crosses. Heavens! What Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did I not make that moment? I began a new to reflect upon my self, I was seiz'd with the same Grief that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd me when we began to be Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55740:13"/> And though time ought to have lessen'd the smart of our Misfortunes, seeing them written by your Hand, was sufficient to make me feel it afresh to the very bottom of my Heart. No, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will ever blot out of my mind what you have suffer'd to defend your Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. I shall ever remember the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy of <hi>Alberick</hi> and <hi>Lotulf</hi> against you. I shall for ever behold a Cruel Uncle, an Abus'd Lover, and an Assassinate. I shall never forget how many Enemies your Wit created you; and how many were jealous of your Glory. I will ever call to mind that high Reputation you had so justly acquir'd, which expos'd you to the Hatred and Malice of the Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Learning. Your Book of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s publickly Condemn'd to the Flames. You were threatned with a perpetual Prison. It was in vain for you to plead your Innocence, and to prove that you were impos'd upon, and that you were accus'd of things you had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver said, or thought. You Condemn'd them your self, but yet all this avail'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing towards your Justification, they would needs have you to be an Heretick right or wrong. Those two false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55740:14"/> who inveigh'd so bitterly against you at the Council of <hi>Rheims,</hi> omitted nothing to ruine you. What Scandals did they not fix on the Name of <hi>Paraclet</hi> which you gave to the Chappel you did Build? What Storm did the Treacherous Monks you honour'd with the Name of Brothers, raise against you? That Chain of Misfortunes has drawn Blood even from the very bottom of my Heart. My Tears which I could no wise stop, have blotted part of your Letter. I could wish they had been able to blot out all the Characters of it in the same manner, to send it you back thus. If <hi>I</hi> could but have kept it a little longer it would have satisfy'd me; but it was taken too soon from me.</p>
               <p>However, it is most certai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and I own it to you, that I was much Calmer before I had read it; but as soon as I had run it over, all my griefs renew'd. I have been too long, cry'd I, I have been too long without Complaining. Since the Rage of our Enemies is still alive; Since Time which commonly disarms the most mortal hatred, cannot disarm them; since your Virtue must needs be persecuted till the Grave serves
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55740:14"/> you for a shelter, tho' perhaps even there their Rage will Rake your Ashes, I will keep your misfortunes for ever present to my mind. I will publish them throughout the World, to disgrace this Age that has not understood you. I will hope for nothing, since all things are against you; and that the World takes a delight in persecuting your Innocence. What? my Memory ever full of your past Misfortunes; must I still dread to see you involv'd in new ones! Must my Dear <hi>Abelard</hi> never be mention'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Tears! Shall his Name never be pronounc'd without a Heart-breaking Sigh! Pray consider the condition to which you have reduc'd me. Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Afflicted, without the least Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation, unless it comes from you. Therefore I do conjure you, do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse it me; but give me a faithful Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all that relates to you. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to know it, tho' never so sad or moving. Perhaps the mixture of my Sighs with yours will ease you, if it be true as it is commonly reported, that Afflictions that are shar'd by others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the more Supportable.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:55740:15"/>
               <p>Do not tell me for an excuse that you are willing to spare our Tears. The Tears of <hi>Recluse Maids</hi> in a Mournful abode of Penitence are not to be spar'd. Besides, should you tarry to write to u<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> until you had some agreeable news to send us, you would tarry too long. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune seldom sides with the Virtuous; and she is so Blind, that it is not to be expected she should distinguish one Wise Man among a Crowd of Fools. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore write to us without expecting those kind of Miracles: They are too rare, and we are destin'd to too many Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes to expect a Change. I propose to my self a world of satisfaction in open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of your Letters, tho' it were only to convince me that you have not forgot me. <hi>Seneca</hi> (which you have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten made me Read) was so sensible, tho' a <hi>Stoick,</hi> of that kind of Joy, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he open'd any from <hi>Lucilla,</hi> he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy'd he enjoy'd all the same pleasure, he did when with her.</p>
               <p>I have observ'd since our absence, that we are much more delighted with the Pictures of those we love, when at a great distance from us, than when they are nearer. Nay more, the farther they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55740:15"/> are from us, their Pictures seem to me to become the more like them: at least our Imagination, which draws them conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually out of a desire to see them again, makes them appear so to us. By an effect which is peculiar to Love, vain Colours, and a little Cloth seem anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us as soon as the belov'd object returns. I have your Picture, and never pass by it without stopping before it; whereas I hardly minded it when you were here. If Painting, which is but a mute representation of Objects, affords so much Pleasure: What Joys do not Letters Inspire? They are Animated; they speak; they have that <hi>Genius</hi> which Explains the Motions of the Heart; they Inclose within them the fire of our Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; they make them as sensible as when we see one another; they express what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we could say, that is Soft and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der when we are together; and being sometimes somewhat bolder, they utter more.</p>
               <p>We may write to one another; that Innocent Pleasure is not forbidden us. Let us not, by our own Neglect, lose the only satisfaction we have remaining, and which perhaps is the only one our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55740:16"/> cannot deprive us of. I will say that you are my Husband; You shall behold me speak like a Wife; and in spight of all your Misfortunes, you shall be whatever you please in a Letter. Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were Invented for the relief of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluse</hi> Persons like my self: Having lost the real Pleasure of seeing and possessing you, I will find it again in some measure, in those you shall write to me. I shall read your most secret Thoughts in them; I will carry them continually about me: Infine, if you are capable of any Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, let it only be by the Caresses I shall make to them; and never grow a Rival unless it be to the happiness of your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: And to avoid all manner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint, write to me without Application, and with Negligence. I would have your Heart speak to me, and not your Wit. I cannot live unless you tell me that you love me still. That Language must needs be so Natural to you, that I do not think you could utter any other to me without Violence: Besides, it is very reasonable you should close up those Wounds, by some marks of a Constant Affection, which you have open'd again in my Soul, by the doleful account you
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55740:16"/> gave your Friend: Not that I blame the Innocent Artifice you have us'd to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort one in Distress, by comparing his Misery to a greater. Charity is Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, and Praise-worthy in those Pious slights: But do you not owe somewhat more to your self than to that Friend, whatever Friendship you may have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted with him? We are call'd your Sisters; we call our selves your Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and if there were more engaging Terms in Nature we would use them to Express our being devoted to you, as also what you owe unto us. Altho' a prudent Silence should cloak our Just acknowledgments, this Church, these Altars, and these Places would declare it sufficiently. But, without suffering Stones and Marble to speak, I confess, and will ever be proud to tell the World, that you are the only Founder of this House. Your coming to this place has render'd it famous, whereas it was only known before for the Robberies &amp; Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that were committed in it. It was a Den of Thieves and Rogues; but you have made it a House of Prayer. These Cloisters are not beholding to publick Alms. The Sins of Publicans are not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55740:17"/> fix'd on their Walls, nor their Vices bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri'd in their Foundations. The God whom we serve in this Place, beholds nothing there but Innocent Riches and Simple Maids, wherewith you have fill'd it. And therefore this young Plantation is wholly indebted to you for what it is: You ought to Cultivate it, and to afford it all your Cares: You ought to make it one of the principal applications of your Life. Although the Grace of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion seems to be intail'd upon it on all parts, by our Cloisters and our Vows: Tho' the points of our Grates are so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Bulwarks to defend the approaches of it; yet whereas the Bark is only co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd in us, that sap of <hi>Adam,</hi> which rises imperceptibly in the Heart, produces Distempers, which wither, and abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ruin the Trees which seem to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise most, unless they be continually grafted. Virtue among us, remains ever grafted upon Nature, which is weak and Inconstant. To Plant the <hi>Vine of the Lord,</hi> is not an ordinary piece of work: it requires more than a Day; and when it is once planted, it requires all our application to preserve it. Does not the Apostle, as great a Workman
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55740:17"/> as he was, tell us, That he has Planted, that <hi>Appollos</hi> has Water'd, and that God has Bless'd the Work, and has made it to grow? <hi>Paul</hi> had planted the Faith among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> by Holy and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Predications; <hi>Apollos,</hi> a zealous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciple of that Great Master, cultivated that Faith, by mild and frequent Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; and the Grace of God, which their continual Cares solicited so pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully to descend upon that People, answer'd their expectation.</p>
               <p>This example ought to regulate your Conduct towards us, I am sensible that you are not idle; but tho' you Labour, you do not Labour for us. You Labour for People whose Thoughts are wholly bent on Earth, and never soar above it; and you refuse your assistance to Persons of a nicer Taste, who are reeling, and do use their utmost endeavours not to fall. You throw the Riches of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel before Swine, in speaking to Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that are fill'd with the Riches of this World, and fatten'd with the juice of the Earth; and at the same time neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Innocent Sheep, who, as nice as they are, would follow you into Desarts and over Mountains. Why do you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55740:18"/> Labour so much for ingrateful Persons? and forget poor Maids, who would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think themselves sufficiently grateful? Must I be afraid to speak in my own Name, and must I imploy other Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers than my own, to obtain something of you? The <hi>Augustins, Tertullians, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romes</hi> have written to <hi>Eudoxa's, Paula's</hi> and <hi>Melanie's;</hi> and when you read those Names, tho' Saints, can you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get mine? Would it be a crime for you to direct me like <hi>St. Jerome,</hi> to Preach to me like <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and to discourse of Grace to me with <hi>St. Augustin?</hi> Your Learning and your Sence ought not to be a barren Soil for me. In writing to me, you writ to a Wife: a Sacrament has render'd that Commerce lawful: And since it is in your Power to satisfie me without committing the least scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, why should you not do it? I have a barbarous Uncle, whose Inhumanity only serves to indear you to my Heart. It serves me instead of all, that the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness and remembrance of our Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures could inspire us with, to make us love each other. You are no longer to be fear'd, do not fly me. Hearken to my Sighs, your being a Witness of them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55740:18"/> will suffice. If I have put my self into a Cloister out of Reason, persuade me to tarry in it out of Devotion. You are the cause of all my Sufferings, how should another ease me.</p>
               <p>You must needs remember, for those that have lov'd can never forget, with what delight I spent whole Days in hearing you? How I us'd to steal away from every body, when we were not to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to write to you? What disquiets did a <hi>Billet</hi> cost me, before it came to your hands? And what shifts were we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to, to gain People to be our Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents? I am sensible these particulars do surprize you. You dread to hear the sequel; but I do no longer blush at it, since my Passion for you has no bounds. I have out done all this for you this day; I have hared my self to love you. I have lost my self here to make you live in quiet. Nothing but Virtue joyn'd to a Passion, free from sensuality, could produce such Effects. Those who love Pleasures, love the Living, not the Dead. We are soon weary of Burning for those that are no longer in a condition to burn for it. My cruel Uncle was sensible of this. He imagin'd that being like other Women,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55740:19"/> I lov'd your Sex better than your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, but his Crime is vain. I love yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> more than ever, I am reveng'd of him by overwhelming you with all my stoo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of tenderness. If the Passion I formerl<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> had for you, was not so pure as it is a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> present: If at that time the Mind an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Body divided in me the pleasure of lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving you; I have told it you a thousan<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> times, I have always been more pleas'd with the possession of your Heart, than with the enjoyment of all that which is the object of the Felicity of our Sex; and of all what was in you, Man wa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> not that which pleas'd me most.</p>
               <p>You ought to be sufficiently convinc'd of it, by the great repugnancy I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd for Marriage. For tho' I was sen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sible that Name was August among Men and Holy in Religion, the thought of ceasing to be free by it, hindred me from finding any charms in it. The Bonds of Marriage, tho' never so Honourable, are attended with a necessary Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whose ties seem to ravish the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Loving; and I was desirous to free a Man, who perhaps would not always love me, from the necessity of loving. I despis'd the name of Wife; to live happy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55740:19"/> with that of a Mistriss. Those niceties of a Maid who lov'd you, with so much tenderness, and yet not so much as she desir'd, were not unknown to you, since you entertain'd your Friend with them in the Letter I have surpriz'd. You told him very well, that I found nothing but what was very insipid in all those publick Ingagements, that form Bonds which nothing but Death can break, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate a dismal necessity of Life and Love: but you did not add, that I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested to you a thousand times, that it was insinitely more pleasing to me to live with <hi>Abelard</hi> as his Mistress, than to be Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press with <hi>Augustus;</hi> and that I preferr'd the happiness of obeying you, before the captivating of the Master of the Uniuerse Lawfully. Riches and Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur are none of the Charms of Love. A real Passion divides the Lover from what is not himself, and lays aside his Fortune, his Rank, his Imployments, to consider him only.</p>
               <p>Those, who seek for an Estate and Dignities, in the cold embraces of a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Husband, do not Love. They aim much more in such a Marriage, to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their Ambition than their Love.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55740:20"/> I grant that such a mercenary Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be attended with some Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Fortune; but I can never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that it is possible thus to enjo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the sensible Pleasures of a tender Union or to feel the secret and charming emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of two Hearts, that have bee<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> long in search of each other to unit<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> themselves. The Martyrs of Marriag<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> hourly sigh for better settlements, whic<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> they think they have lost. The Wif<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> sées Husbands richer than her own. Th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Husband, Wives with better Fortune<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> than his. Mercenary Ingagements cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Regrets, and those Regrets Discord. They design to be parted, or at least they wish it. That insatiate devouring desire, is the Avenger of Love, whic<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> they injure in expecting to meet a hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piness by Love, besides Love it self. If there be any real Felicity on Earth, I am persuaded, that it is only to be found in the Union of two Persons, who love each other with freedom, whom a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ination has joyn'd, and whom an equal Merit has satisfy'd. Then there is no vacuity in their Hearts. All is at rest there, because all is contain'd.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:55740:20"/>
               <p>Could I believe you were as well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suaded of my Merit, as I am of yours, I would tell you, that there was a time in which we might have been reckon'd in the number of those Happy ones. Ah! How could I chuse but be persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of your Merit? Tho' I had been willing to question it; the universal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem the World had for you, would have convinc'd me. Is there a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Province or City, that has not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sir'd to have you? Did you ever remove from any place, without being attended with the Heart and Eyes of those you left behind you? Every body was proud of saying, <hi>I have seen</hi> Abelard <hi>to day.</hi> The very Women, notwithstanding the rigid Laws the World has impos'd upon them, could not forbear expressing, that they felt something for you beyond common Esteem. I have known some, who prais'd their Husbands exceedingly and yet were jealous of my Joys, and show'd sufficiently that you might have expected every thing from them. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, who was capable to resist you? Your Reputation which flatter'd the Vanity of our Sex; Your Air; Your Behaviour; Those lively Eyes in which your Soul
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55740:21"/> was so admirably Drawn; Your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, which a natural simplicity and delicacy render'd so agreeable and insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating; In fine, every thing spoke in favour of you Very different, in that from those who by knowing too much; have not Art to trifle agreeably; and who with all their Wit cannot gain the Heart of Women, who have not near so great a share of it as they.</p>
               <p>With what Ease did you compose Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses? and yet those learned Amusements which only serv'd to refresh you after a more serious Study, are the Delight of the most Ingenuous; and there are none among them, who do not judge you worthy of that <hi>Rose</hi> you have so ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously explain'd. Even the most incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Songs, and other Trifles you have written for me, have a thousand Charms, and a thousand Beauties in them. I will make them last, while Love endures. Thus what you only design'd for me, will be Sung for others; and those Words, so natural and so ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which were witnesses of your Love in slight Verses, and little Songs, will serve others to explain themselves much better than otherwise they could
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55740:21"/> have done. How many Rivals have those kind of Gallantry's created me? How many Beauties have endeavour'd to apply them to themselves? It was an Homage which Self-Love render'd to their Charms. How 'many I have seen who declar'd themselves for you by their Sighs, when they were told, after an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Visit you had made them, that they were the <hi>Silvia</hi>'s of your Verses? Others out of despair have often reproachfully told me, That I had no other Beauty but what your Verses gave me, nor any advantages over them, but that of being belov'd by you. Notwithstanding Self-Love, which is so natural in all Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, I thought my self happy in a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to whom I was indebted for all my Charms; and I was transported with Joy to think, that I was serv'd by a Man, who had the power to make a Goddess of his Mistriss. Flattering my self with your Glory, I read, with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaisance, the Charms you gave me, and often without consulting, found my self what you were pleas'd to speak me, the better to please you.</p>
               <p>But alas! that time is past; I now weep for the loss of my Lover, and the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55740:22"/> only thing that is remaining of all my Joys, is but a Remembrance which kills me. You who were jealous of my hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, know that he whom you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy'd me, is no longer for you, nor for me. I have lov'd him; my Love is his Crime, and has occasion'd his Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. My small Perfections had charm'd him; pleas'd with each other, we liv'd happy, and quietly, and pass'd the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of our Days. If it was a Crime to live thus, that Crime pleases me still, and my only Despair is to find my self Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. But my misfortune is to have had unjust Parents, whose Rage and Hatred have disturb'd the Calm in which we liv'd. Had those Barbarians call'd back their Reason, I should now be in quiet with my Husband. What cruelty could equal theirs, when a blind Fury ingag'd them to hire a Murtherer to surprize you asleep? Had I been with you, I would have defended you at the cost of my own Life: My Cries alone would have stopp'd his Arm. But in this place Love is offended, and my Modesty joyn'd to my despair, stops my Tongue. It is not proper for me to say all I think up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Subject; and tho' it were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55740:22"/> I could not do it. Besides, there is <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> great deal of Eloquence in silence, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hen misfortunes are too great to be express'd.</p>
               <p>Tell me only, for this is one of my <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>reatest afflictions, why you have begun <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o neglect me, since my Profession? <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ou know that I had no other induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ents for it but your misfortunes, nor <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ther consent for it but what you gave <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e. Let us hear the Cause of your coldness, or at least permit me to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover my Thoughts to you. Is it not, perhaps, that Pleasure only was your <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>im, in applying your self to me, and that my Passion which left no room for Desires in you, has diminish'd your Flame? Thou didst please unfortunate <hi>Eloisa,</hi> when thou didst not desire to please: thou didst deserve assiduites, when thou oughtst to have rejected them, and Incense, when thou didst push back the Arm that offer'd it to thee. But since thy Heart has suffer'd it self to be mov'd; is grown soft, and has sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render'd it self, since thou hast sacrific'd thy self, since thou hast bury'd thy self alive, thou art forsaken, thou art forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. A woful Experience has convinc'd
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55740:23"/> me, that People fly those they are too much oblig'd too, and that the greatest Favours sooner create coldness in Men, than Gratitude. And indeed, this weak Heart made too slight a defence to be long dear to you. You took it with ease, you quit it in the same manner. But ingrateful as you are, I will never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to it; and tho'. I ought not to have a Will in this place, I have nevertheless preserv'd that of being belov'd by you. In pronouncing my sad Vows, I had the <hi>Last Billet</hi> you writ to me about me; by which you assur'd me, you would ever be mine, and that you would only Live to Love me. Therefore it was to you I offer'd my self: You had my Heart: I had yours, do not require any thing back from me, and suffer my Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as a thing that is yours, and which you cannot part from.</p>
               <p>Alas! How weak am I to talk thus? Our Object here is a God, and I only speak of a Man: You force me to it, Cruel! by your behaviour: You are the only cause of my fault. False Man! Was it Just thus to cease to love me all of a sudden? Why did you not deceive me a while, instead of abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55740:23"/> me absolutely? Had you only gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>en me some weak signs of a dying Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>on, I should have endeavour'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eive my self, to believe you had some <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>onstancy. But after the rate you use <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e, what Opinion can I have of you? What can I think of a forgetfulness like <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ours? And by a forgetfulness of this <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ature, do not you even take away from <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e all means of writing to you? I passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nately desire to see you; but if I am <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>orbidden to hope it, I will content my <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>elf with a few Lines from your hand. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s it then so hard a task to write to what we love, if it be true that you still love me? I desire none of your learned Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ers, on which your Reputation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ends. I only desire some of those <hi>Billets</hi> that proceed from the Heart; which the Pen can hardly follow, and Wit has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with. How was I deceiv'd, when I thought you wholly mine, in receiving the <hi>Veil,</hi> and by engaging my self to live Eternally under your Laws. For in making my Vows, I only meant to be entirely yours; and I voluntarily submitted to the desire you express'd to see me lockd up for ever. There<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, nothing but Death▪ can make me
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55740:24"/> abandon the place in which you plac'd me, Nay, my very Ashes will remain in it, in expectation of yours, or the longer to shew you my Obedience. Why should I conceal the secret of my Vocation? You know it; it was neither my Zeal nor my Devotion that plac'd me in a Cloister. Your Conscience is too faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a Witness of it for you to disown it. Yes, it was the Flesh and not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that transported me into this place. I am in it; I Live in it; I remain in it; an unfortunate Love, and cruel Parents condemn me to it; and if I have not the continuation of your Cares, if I lose your Friendship, what will be the Fruit of my Prison? What recompence can I hope for? The unfortunate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequences of a Criminal Conduct, and your particular Disgraces, have cover'd me with a chaste Habit, but not with the sincere Desire of a real Repentance. Thus I combat and Jabour in vain. I am among the Spouses of a God, the Servant of a Man; Among the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Slaves of his Cross, the weak Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of a prophane Love. I am at the head of a community of Nuns, only devoted to <hi>Abelard.</hi> My God: Why
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55740:24"/> do you not direct me? Is it your Grace that makes me speak these Words, or is it only my Despair that forces them from me? At least I feel my self in the Temple of Chastity only cover'd with the Fire that has Inflam'd us. I view my self in it, I confess like a Sinner; but one who far from weeping for her Sins, only weeps for her Lover, and who through a weakness unworthy of her present condition, only calls to mind her past actions, not being able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on any others.</p>
               <p>Oh Heavens! What dismal Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are these? I upbraid my self with my faults; I accuse you of yours: and why all this? <hi>Veil'd</hi> as I am what disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders do you occasion? It is a cruel task always to struggle for Duty against In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination. I am very sensible of what I owe to the <hi>Veil</hi> that covers me; but I feel much better yet, what a long habit of Loving can effect on a sensible Heart. I am subdu'd; I am Vanquish'd by my Inclination. My Passion disorders my Mind and Will. One Moment I listen to the Sentiments of Piety that arrise within me, and the next I suffer all the Charms of my Tenderness to Reign in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55740:25"/> my Imagination. I tell you now a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand things I would not have told you yesterday. I was resolv'd no longer to Love you; I consider'd that I had made Vows; that I was <hi>Veil'd,</hi> dead, and as it were buried; But there arises by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees from the bottom of my Heart a Trouble which destroys all those Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and clouds my Reason and my Piety. You Reign in Places so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd, and so Imperceptible in that Heart, that I cannot attack you in them; and when I think of breaking the Bonds that Engage me to you, I flatter my self, and all the efforts I am capable of, only serve to tie 'em closer. Oh! for pity sake, assist a Wretch to renounce her desires, her self, and you if Possible. If you are a Lover, if you are a Father, Succour a Mistress, Comfort a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Cannot those Names, those Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Names, move you? Yield, Oh yield, to pity, or to Love! If you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to it, I am ready to be <hi>a real Nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and will no longer prophane my Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I am ready to humble my self with you before the Richess of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of my God, who makes use of all things for our Sanctification, who
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55740:25"/> through an effect of his Grace purifies whatever is Vicious and Corrupted in our Principles, who through an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Inconceivable Mercy, worthy of him alone, almost forces us, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens our Eyes to give us a glimpse of so many favours which we refus'd to know.</p>
               <p>I design'd to end here; but while I am angry with you, I must disburthen my Heart, and tell you how far it suspects, how much it Upbraids you. I must needs confess to you, that it shook my very Soul to find, that, after we had both resolv'd to consecrate our selves to God, you engag'd me to do it, before you. What? <hi>said I,</hi> does he fear to see the Example of <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife, who look'd behind her in quitting <hi>Sodom,</hi> reviv'd in me? If my Youth, and my Sex, could make you fearful that I might go back to the World, especially <hi>Paris</hi> not being yet on Fire, nor reduc'd to Ashes, my Behaviour, my Fidelity, and this Heart, which you too well knew, ought to have cur'd you of all those sorts of Suspicious. That suspicious Precaution touches me sensibly. What? cry'd I, heretofore my bare word suffic'd to assure him, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55740:26"/> now can nothing less than a God and Vows secure him that I will be true.</p>
               <p>What cause have I ever given him to suspect me of the least Fickleness? I never refus'd to meet him at all his Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous; and should I scruple to follow him in Houses of Sanctity! What? I who have made my self the <hi>Victim</hi> of pleasure to satisfie him, could I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to be an <hi>Oblation</hi> of Honour to obey him! Has Vice then such Charms over well-born Souls, that after having drank in the <hi>Cup</hi> of Sins, one could not receive the <hi>Chalice</hi> of Sanctity without regret? Or else did you think your self a better Master for Vice than for Virtue? Did you think that it was Easier to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade me to the first than to the latter? No, that doubt would be too Injurious to us both. Virtue is too beautiful not to Embrace it where it is met; and Vice is too Ugly not to shun it, when you make it known. All things are Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me which you desire: Nothing is dreadful or difficult to me when you appear. I am only Weak when you do not guide me: Therefore 'tis in your Power to mould me as you please. Had you any thing to fear, you would be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55740:26"/> less Negligent. I have done too much, and I must now Triumph over your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude. While we Liv'd happy, you might have reason to doubt, whither it was not Pleasure that Engag'd me to you, rather than Friendship. But now the Place from whence I write decides it. I Love you here at least as much as I did in the World. Had I been in Love with Voluptuousness, after your Misfortune, I might easily have found wherewith to have satisfy'd my self. I was then but 20 Years of Age, and there were still Men enough rcmaining whom I might have hop'd to please; but <hi>Abe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd</hi> was gone, and I desir'd no other: Therefore 'tis only for your sake, that in an Age so proper for Love, I Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over Love it self, by burying my self alive in a Monastery. It is to you I Dedicate these remainders of Beauty which the Solitary Days and Nights I pass hasten to Ternish: But since you cannot Enjoy them, I take them back from you, to offer them to God, and thus make him a second Present of my Heart, of my Days, and of my Life.</p>
               <p>I enlarge a little too much in this Place, and I ought not to put you so
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55740:27"/> much in mind of your Misfortunes, an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of what I suffer for your sake. We Ternish the Splendor of the greate<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Actions when we make the Tediou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Panegyrick of them our selves; Bu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that when we are to deal with Person who are doz'd by a base Ingratitude we can never repeat what we have don<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> for them too much. Were you of tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Number that Reproach would tell you a World of things. But I do not direct it to you, lest you should prove one of them. Wavering as I am, I am sensible that I love you still. However I ca<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> hope for nothing. I have renounc'd Life. Yet tho' depriv'd of all, I feel that I have not renounc'd <hi>Abelard</hi> in losing my Lover. I preserve all my Love in a Monastery, where I keep all my Vows. Our Rigid Laws have not depriv'd me of Humanity. You have not turn'd me into Marble by making me change my Habit. My Heart is not harden'd, tho' you are absent from me. I am as sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as I was heretofore, and yet I ought no longer to be so. Suffer, without blemish to your Empire, that my Lover may Exhort me to Live under your Laws. Your Yoke will be Lighter, if
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55740:27"/> his Hand supports it. Our Exercises <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ill become Lovely to me, if he will <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ouchsafe to shew me the Usefulness of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hem. Retirement, Solitude, you will <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e no longer dismal, If I may hear that <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> have a place in his Remembrance. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. Heart that has been so sensible as <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hine cannot easily resolve to grow In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ifferent. We Hate, we Love, several <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mes before we can attain Tranquility; <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd we still preserve some distant hopes <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>f not being absolutely forgotten.</p>
               <p>Yes, <hi>Abelard,</hi> I do conjure thee, by <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>he Chains I drag in this Place, to ease <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>he weight of them, and to render them <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s pleasing to me as I could wish them. Give me Maxims of holy Love.▪ After <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aving quitted thee, I am proud of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ng the Spouse of a God; my Heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ores that Title, and disdains all others. Teach me how that Divine Love is bred, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aintain'd, and purifies it self more and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ore. When we were both in the Sea of this World, your Vein was continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lly Imploy'd to acquaint the World with our Joys and Pleasures; But now we <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re in the Harbor of Grace, is it not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable you should speak with me of my Happiness, and teach me what may In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55740:28"/> it? Have the same complaisance for me in my present Condition, as you had in the World. Without changing our Hearts, let us change our Object Laying aside prophane Songs, let us sing Divine Hymns. Let us Elevate ou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Hearts to God; and let us have n<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Transports, but for his Glory.</p>
               <p>I expect this from you, as a thing you cannot refuse. Heaven has a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Right over the hearts of the Grea<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Men he has form'd. Whenever he touches them he Transports them, and they Languish for, and talk of nothing but him. Until that moment of Grace arrives, think on me, and do not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get me; Remember my Affection, my Fidelity, and my Constancy. Love a Mistress, Cherish a Daughter, a Sister, a Spouse. Consider that I love you still, and that I Combat no longer to Love you. Heaven! What a word is this? What design? I Tremble; my Heart Revolts against my Words, and being ready to blot them out, I conclude this long Letter, bidding you, if you desire it (and would to God I could do it my self) Farewel for Ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:55740:28"/>
               <head>My Lady <hi>C</hi>— to her Cousin <hi>B</hi>— of the <hi>Temple,</hi> Esq; After having received from him a Copy of Verses on her Beauty. <hi>LETTER II.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Cousin,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours with the Verses en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed, and here return you my hearty thanks for the Face, the Shape, the Meen, which you have so generously bestow'd upon me. From looking upon your Verses I went to my Glass, but Jesu! the difference, tho' I bought it to Flatter me, yet compared to you, I found it a Plain-Dealer. It shew'd me immediately, that I have been a great deal more beholden to you, than I have been to Nature; for she only formed me not frightful, but you have made me Divine. But as you have been a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:55740:29"/> great deal kinder than Nature has bee<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to me▪ I think my self obliged in requ<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tal, to be a good deal more liberal tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Heaven has been to you, and to allo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> you as large a share of Wit, as you hav<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> given me of Beauty. Since so hone<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> a Gentleman as your self, has stretche<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> his Conscience to commend my Perso<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> I am bound in Gratitude to do violenc<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to my Reason to extol your Verses When I left the Town, I desir'd you t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> furnish me with the News of the Place<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and the first thing that I have receiv'd from you, is a Copy of Verses on my Beauty, by which you dextrously inferr, that the most extraordinary piece o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> News which you can send me, is, to tell me that I am handsom: by which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious inference you had infallibly brought the scandal of a Wit upon you, if your Verses had not stood up in your justification. But (tell me, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sin), Could you think I should prove so easy a Creature, as to believe all that you have said of me? How could you find in your Heart to make such a fool of me, and such a cheat of your self, to intoxicate me with flattery, and draw me into truck my little stock
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55740:29"/> of Wit and Judgment for a meer ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of Beauty, when the real thing too falls infinite short, of what you would make me exchange for the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of it? for (Cousin) there is this considerable difference, between the merit of Wit and Beauty, that Men are never violently influenc'd by Beauty, unless it has weaken'd their Reason, and never feel halfe the force of Wit, unless their Judgments are sound; the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal time in which those of your Sex admire Beauty in ours, is between Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen and Thirty, that is, after they are past their Innocence, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are come to their Judgments: and have not you now (Cousin) been commending a very pretty quality, to admire which, as I have just shewn you, supposes, not only a corrupted Will, but a raw understanding: besides, How frail, How transitory is it! Nature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives us of it at Thirty. If Diseases spare it till then; by which constant proceeding she seems to imply, that she gives it as a Gugaw, to please us in the Childhood of our Reason, and takes it from us, as a thing below us, when we come to years of discretion. Thus
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55740:30"/> Cousin, you have been commending<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> quality which hath nothing of true M<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit in it: and of which I have no grea<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter a share, than to keep me from bein<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> scandalous. so that all that I could ha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> got by your kindnesse, if I had parte<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> with my Judgment, in order to reap t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> benefit of it, had been nothing h<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> wretched Conceit, and ridiculous A<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectation. If I thought you had enoug<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of the Gallant Man in you, to take wh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> I say in good part, I would advise y<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to engage no further in Poetry.<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ruled by a Woman for once, and min<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> your <hi>Cook upon Littleton:</hi> rather Pettifo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> than Flatter. For if you are resolved<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be a Cheat, you will shew at least som<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Conscience, in choosing rather to chows<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> People of their Money, than to bubb<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> them of their Understanding: Besid<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Cousin, you have not a Genius whic<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> will make a great Poet, and be please<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to consider, that a small Poet is a scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, Wight, that indifferent Verse<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> are very bad ones, and that an insipi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Panegyrick upon another, is a severe Libel on your self. Besides, there wil<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> start up a Satyrist, one day, and then▪ woe be to cold Rhymery; Old <hi>Englan<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:55740:30"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not yet so barren, but there will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ise some generous Spirit, who, besides <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> stock of Wit, and good Sence (which <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re no very common qualities) will not <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nly be furnished with a sound Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ent, which is an extraordinary Talent, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ut with a true Taste for Eloquence and Wit, which is scarce any where to be <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ound, and which comprehends, not <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nly a just discernment, but a fine Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>etration, and a delicate Criticism; such <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Satyrist as this, Cousin, must arise, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd therefore, you had best take care <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y a judicious silence, that whenever he appears, he may be sure to divert you, and not afflict you.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I Am</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:55740:31"/>
               <head>From a Lady in the Country, to a Gentleman in Town. <hi>LETTER III.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear, thô unkind, SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HAD the Torment of Separation been equal on both sides, you could not have forgot me so long, nor conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued silent to my melancholy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints. Absence, is one of the hardest Penalties Love has to undergoe; and would be intolerable, were it not eas'd by the Comfort of mutual Letters; which since I have been so long bereav'd of, I leave it to your self to imagine (if you have a Heart like mine to judge by) How disconsolately I spin out the tedious Hours of weary Life; for since the only Comfort the World affords me, is Absent, What can I find that it should be worth while to live for? since my Life is no longer valuable to me, than 'twill be pleasing to you. There are a Thousand Thoughts conspire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55740:31"/> a Lovers Quiet, and every thing contributes to make Absence unhappy. How often upon the fear of your Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constancy, have I sate down and wept at the Imagination, then pleaded the cause of Love between us, and persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my easie Heart, that you would ne'r be false? How often have Sigh'd at the dreadful apprehension, that some more happy Lover had taken you from the Thoughts of me? Then lookt into my Heart upon your lovely Image, and fancy'd 'twas still the same, still con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant and loving as before? Thus do I plead in your behalfe, and study to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince my Heart, that our Loves will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have an end but with our Days; thus do I wear away the tedious Days, taking delight in none, but in the hopes of that which will let us meet again, and make me once more happy,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Who am <hi>Your entirely Affectionate, and Constant Lover.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>The Sorrows of our Absence have made me Poetical.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:55740:32"/>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>HOW well I always Lov'd you know,</l>
                     <l>Since first your Charms did move;</l>
                     <l>But what for you I undergoe,</l>
                     <l>None knows but▪ I and love.</l>
                     <l>Could you but see the endless smart</l>
                     <l>Which wretched <hi>Caelia</hi> bears,</l>
                     <l>Those Eyes which set on fire her Heart,</l>
                     <l>Wou'd quench it with their Tears.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>But distance from her Love keeps</l>
                     <l>Poor <hi>Caelia</hi>'s in cruel pain,</l>
                     <l>And she laments, and Sighs, and weeps,</l>
                     <l>His Absence, but in vain.</l>
                     <l>The doom you gave my Heart to prove,</l>
                     <l>I know have doubled found.</l>
                     <l>You only left it burnt in Love,</l>
                     <l>But now in Tears 'tis Drown'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="letter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:55740:32"/>
               <head>From a Lady to a Gentleman, who after a long Converse with her, and Promises of an entire and lasting Affection, was going to be Married to another. <hi>LETTER IV.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>FOR how can I forget those soft Names by which my Affection has taught me to call you; or how can I alter my Language since I have never known how to speak to you in any, since our first Converse, but that of Love? But possibly now you understand it not, or are willing to forget that e'er you did; and cannot bear the Remembrance of that unfortunate Woman, whose Crime was not that she Lov'd, but that she
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55740:33"/> Lov'd too well. Yet I shall not at all complain of your Unkindness, nor tax you with falshood for breaking Promises which, may be, you ne'r intended should be kept; but bend all my loud Sorrows against the Injustice of my Fate, which has given me so large a stock of Love, and been so scanty in Deserts, as not to allow me wherewithal to merit a Return. Nor can I blame your new Choice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Person every way Meritorious; yet give me leave, when I hear she is in Possession of that Happiness which I was so frail to hope once would be mine for ever, give me leave to Sigh to my self, and say to my Heart with a relent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Thought, Is this the end of all my glorious Hopes? and are my delightful Expectations terminated thus? Must my entire Affection serve for nothing but an Instrument of my Misery, and was my Passion ever true, only that <hi>I</hi> might be made Eternally unhappy? Then if my crowded Sorrows break forth in Tears, give me leave to mourn to my self, and deny me not the Privilege of Grief, who have for ever taken from me all hopes of Joy: My Sighs will not reach your happy Ears, nor disturb the peaceable
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55740:33"/> Enjoyment of your new Love; nor do I desire they should; there is some sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction even in being unhappy, since it pleases you I should be so; and I will study to bear my Misery with what Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience <hi>I</hi> can, since you have thought fit to Doom me to it, and ever acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that there is a Crime in loving too well: The worst Wish <hi>I</hi> have for you, is, that the Lady may Love you as well as <hi>I</hi> did, and when you find your self happy in such Affection, give me leave to hope, that sometime or other you will think, (however our cruel Stars ordain'd it) that such a Lover deserv'd a Better Fate; and if ever you cast away a Thought upon so Unfortunate a thing as my self, remember that as <hi>I</hi> always Lov'd you above the World, so I must continue to my Grave</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your still Constant, tho' Unhappy, Lover.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="letter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:55740:34"/>
               <head>Phryne <hi>to</hi> Eugenia <hi>agains<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Marriage. LETTER V.</head>
               <p>I Receiv'd yours, my <hi>Eugenia,</hi> by the last Post, in which you give me ar<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Account of the Addresses of <hi>Lysander.</hi> You might have spar'd your Character of him; he's too well known to our Sex in this City to want his Picture to be sent us out of the Country; his Wit, his Gaiety, fine Person, and all his other Accomplishments have made more, than you, sigh for him in spight of his being Married. Whatever Sentiments a Lady has of the Addresses of a Married Man, before she sees him, she yet wishes for those of <hi>Lysander,</hi> as soon as she beholds or hears him speak. You have therefore a happiness beyond thousands in having captivated his Heart, and if you deny your self the use of it, you owe your
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55740:34"/> own Misery to your own foolish and capricious humour. Ah! How many Ladies of my Acquaintance sigh for, and have in vain endeavour'd to gain that Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, Fortune has voluntarily thrown into your Arms! But he's Married you say, and therefore you can't be happy, you can't Enjoy your Wishes without a Crime; you can't be his Wife, and you resolve you'l not be what you dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain to Name. <hi>I</hi> know not what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence Custom may have on you; but I'm not at all mortified at those ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Notions the Vulgar have, of having an Intrigue with a Man without the Priests Licence. For my part, <hi>Eugenia, I</hi> think the desire of Marriage is more Unreasonable and Unnatural, than that of Traytors, for 'tis immediately; and knowingly to conspire against our own <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Happiness. Love</hi> sows the gilded Paths of Youth, with a thousand soft and melting Pleasures; but Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age comes, and with one fatal blast blows them all away, and it makes us Old in the very dawn of Youth; for not to Love is to be Old, and to Marry is the certain way not to Love. If Love's a Golden Dream, why should we quit the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55740:35"/> dear Delusion, (when in our own power to avoid it) to Wake to Horror, Misery, and Distraction? That is, why should we Marry? 'Tis true, we read in Novels, and Romances of Lovers faithfuls and constant, nay obstinate Adorer of the Wishing fair one, in spight of all the obstacles of Fortune, Friends, or Rivals; but <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> these Politick Writers lead 'em no farther than Marriage in that humour. When they have brought the Knight and the Damsel to the Noose, they there leave 'em; all the Golden Scenes of Love are over, and there remains no more happiness to describe. If they cou'd shew us any persevering Lover after Marriage, they would do wonders; tho' 'twould be so unnatural, 'twould pass for downright Farce. Marriage in my mind is at best but like the drunken Feasts of the Lapithites; the Mirth, Jolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Pleasure of the Pompous Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet soon degenerates into Strifes and Combats. Love and Constancy have their Reign before Marriage, but the very Words that seek to tye us faster to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, immediately (like the Medicines of Quacks) have a quite contrary Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55740:35"/> and Eternally divide us. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and your own Heart has chose you an object of your desires, whom you can't, according to Custom, Marry, such a sure provision has Fate made for your Happiness; and you like a froward Child slight the mighty gift. But you're affraid of the Curse and Infamy of an Old Maid; first <hi>I</hi> shall little value the opinion of the World, if they think me what, to my own real experimental knowledge, <hi>I</hi> am not; Next, where's the necessity of acting so imprudently, as to hinder your Marriage hereafter? Nature has given us Desires and Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, and added a vast Pleasure to the very Act of their Satisfaction, which shews it can be no ill. All the dictates of Nature are easie, sure, and plain, and we comply with 'em with Pleasure; but the inventions of Whimsical Men, that oppose these, are not follow'd without pain, without constraint, and a thousand inquietudes; by this judge of the Good or Ill of complying with our Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This is no plea for Prostitution, for then is pleasure, the constant Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Natural Actions lost: There are no more Kaptures, no more Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sporting
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55740:36"/> Joys, and Melting Languish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; all is dead, heavy, and insipid, if not Painful and Nauseous. A mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Exercise affords Pleasure and Delight, but continual Toil and Labour is not undertaken without Necessity. The same will hold in all things. 'Tis Non-sense to imagine, that, if Love will not make you happy, a few Canonical Words will do the feat. But <hi>I</hi> have been te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, if this don't please you; and long enough if it does; 'tis in your power to be Happy if you will, for how long I know not; but this I know, if we must seek no Happiness here, but what's lasting, we may be Miserable all our Lives; for the most permanent we can't grasp a Minute longer than Fate pleases. My dear <hi>Eugenia, Adieu.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="letter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:55740:36"/>
               <head>From a Lady to a Gentleman, confessing her Love, which had for some time pass'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Friendship. <hi>LETTER VI.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THE Acquaintance I have had with the Generosity of your Temper, has made me hope, that you will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me a fault I cannot help commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; and excuse what I write; since 'tis in obedience to an Affection that I have not power to resist. Pardon, if I tell you, the Friendship that has been between us has on my side, chang'd its name, and is become something that I dare not trust my Tongue to tell you; yet I doubt not but my frailty has too plainly discover'd it self, and something beyond Friendship has appear'd in all my Actions; which I hope you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strue no farther, than that your poor
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:55740:37"/> Friend has only sinn'd against the Rules of her Sex, and committed a Crime which carries its own punishment along with it: Yet, if Love be a Crime, I am so vain to hope, you will give me leave to be guilty of it, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn me for a fault, which the Charms of your own Person have made me commit. If this open confession of a Frailty, which ought to have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd, be an offence, which Generosity cannot pardon, I am doubly miserable; and wish it still lay buried in that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Breast which gave it Birth; that I might rather carry it with me silently to Death, than let it appear to molest the Peace of one I love above the World: yet be not troubled, Sir, for if the Heart, which bears your Image, be so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate, as not to be so acceptable to you; leave it to it self, and 'twill soon revenge your quarrel, and punish it self for the crime of Loving, which yet it will be guilty of till death, and when e'er it dies, carry to the Grave an Affection that cannot end but with the unhappy Life of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your more than Loving Friend,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="letter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:55740:37"/>
               <head>From a Lady to her Friend, sent with the following Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. <hi>LETTER VII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT Grieves me very sensibly, my Dear Child, that the Sympathy, which is betwixt us in every thing else, should be wanting in that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns me most nearly: that whilst I am doom'd Eternally subject to the Laws of Love, you shou'd maintain so fierce a War against 'em, and not allow the least share of Reason to those who are govern'd by him. It can't satisfie me that you make an exception for me; I must reconcile you to my fellow Slave, before I believe you have the charity to think I have preserv'd my Reason with my Love: For I know Fate has not done a Miracle for me; and you must
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:55740:38"/> either believe I am out of my Wits, o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that Love and Reason are consistent▪ Don't think I have any design agains<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> your Liberty. I own that Freedom t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> more pleasing than the noblest Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and I wou'd not deprive you o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> yours, even for the sake of having yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> agree with me in all things. All I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of you, is, to own that you shun Love more for uneasiness, than the folly of it. And sure you can't deny me that, when I have allow'd you so much: but that I may not give you a new Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment against me, by endeavouring to bring you over to a party, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing you of the Injustice of it: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spairing to do it with my own Reasons, I have been at the pains to Translate the Dialogue, which I send you enclos'd. If you understood the Original, perhaps it might have a better effect upon you: but tho' I cou'd not imitate the Authors Wit, and that pretty, easie, gentile way he has of Writing, I have done my part to give you his Sence. 'Twas writ in <hi>French</hi> by Monsieur <hi>le Pays,</hi> whom you have often heard me commend, and wish you understood him; there is so much Flame and Spirit in his Letters,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:55740:38"/> and most of his Verses, and yet they are written in such a natural and unaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Stile, as shews him to be a Man of a great Genius: his design in this Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue is to justifie Love in those things which seem most extravagant and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable; and sure, if there is any colour of excuse for them, you can't but be reconcil'd to those who ground their Affections well? 'Twas sent by the Author to one of his Mistrisses, whom he calls <hi>Calista:</hi> and since all he says in it of her is due to you, give me leave to apply it, and to hope that since Reason never forsakes you, and that you create Love in all that see you, so fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent a communication may make 'em less Enemies to one another. With this expectation I leave you to be better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd by Mr. <hi>le Pays;</hi> and so make haste to tell you, Dear <hi>Calista,</hi> that whatever effect he may produce upon you, you shall always share my Heart with <hi>Cl—n.</hi> and that as long as I am <hi>O—a.</hi> I shall be</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="dialogue">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:55740:39"/>
               <head>A DIALOGUE BETWIXT <hi>LOVE</hi> and <hi>REASON.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>IT was very difficult for us, agreeable Enemy, to meet in any place but at <hi>Calista</hi>'s: you always fly me so obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, and I have endeavour'd so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>successfully to accost you, that I could never have obtain'd my wish, if Fate had not conducted you to her; but 'twas impossible to shun me there, for I never abandon her, and now I'm resolv'd not to lose so favourable an occasion. Whilst I have you here, I will tell you a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred things that lye at my Heart; I will ask you, why you hate me so vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, and if there be no means for us to be reconcil'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:55740:39"/>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>I don't know, Madam, what cause you have to complain; I do not flie you; I am not your Enemy; and I never, that I can remember, was out of your company; much on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, I always make you my Judge in all my Quarrels; I bring you to justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my Conduct; and in fine, I make use of you in every thing I undertake.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>How dare you maintain so great a falshood to me? you, who chace me from every place where you enter; who are never satisfi'd whilst I take up the least part of a Soul which you wou'd subject: you, who grow angry when I resist you, and who despise me so much, that you will not hear me speak, when I complain of the disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and of the violence you do me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, Madam, I maintain what I have said: Is't not making you a Judge of my Quarrels, when I oblige a Lover who loves without being belov'd, to appeal
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:55740:40"/> to you for the injustice which is do<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> him? Is't not appealing to you to just<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fie his Conduct, when he says 'tis re<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sonable to love that which is lovely and is't not making use of you in<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> actions, when in stealing a Kiss,<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> some other Favour, he maintains th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Reason counsels to pay ones self, wi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> the fortune of one who refuses to pay<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>I grant indeed, that you sometim<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> make use of my Name, but never of m<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Self. Since I am welcome in all plac<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> which are not infected by you, or t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> other Passions. that I am almost a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ways desir'd, and that you are as mu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dreaded as I am wish'd for. You a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> glad to employ my Name when yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> wou'd enter any where, that you ma<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> the sooner gain admittance; but as soo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> as ever you are admitted, you easily di<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cover that I'm not with you, and th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> you hardly know me, or if you do<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> all the use you make of your knowledge is to fly from me, or to drive me from you. If at any time I resolve to com<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bate you, when you have attack'd on<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> that I govern'd; your flatteries imme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diately
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:55740:40"/> prevail with the Senses to revolt <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>gainst me: You intrench your self in <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>heir Post, and then their support makes <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ou so bold, and yours makes them so <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>trong, that all my Darts are broke or <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>lunted, without wounding you in the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>east. 'Tis to no purpose <hi>I</hi> stir and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ake a Noise; call Honour and Duty <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>o my aid; all my resistance becomes <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ain, <hi>I</hi> sink in the end, and must resign <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>he place to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>You tell me, Madam, that <hi>I</hi> sometimes <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ake use of your name, but never of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>our self; and <hi>I</hi> answer to this, and to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ll the other Reproaches which you make me, that on the contrary <hi>I</hi> often Combat the Name, but <hi>I</hi> never Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>at you. 'Tis true, in many Hearts <hi>I</hi> find false Maxims, dangerous Opinions, and ridiculous abuses, which having as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum'd your Name, have also the inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to resist me, and to deny me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into those Hearts, which they have possess'd themselves of. Then knowing 'em to be Enemies that have taken your Name, tho' they do not belong to you, I do my utmost endeavours to destroy
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:55740:41"/>
'em. <hi>I</hi> neglect no advantage; and seeing that they seek Protectors in their Quarrels, that they always interress in their party evil Custom, stupid Shame, and false Glory: By their Example <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> engage the Senses and the Pleasures to my aid, who have lov'd me long, and who are inseparable Friends. With thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> support <hi>I</hi> undertake the Combat, and am almost always certain of Victory: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rout my Enemies, who without wearing your Livery, have the Insolence to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they belong to you, and to engage against me under false Ensigns: So that, Madam, <hi>I</hi> revenge your Quarrel, as we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as my own.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>You are ingenious in defending your self; but yet your excuses are very weak▪ How can you know, that the Enemies you Combat with are not of my Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, since you don't know my Livery, and that perhaps you don't know me, who am always at the head of those you call false Maxims, dangerous Opinions, and ridiculous abuses? but you are a Young rash one, that strike without knowing who; who neither considers
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:55740:41"/> Honour, Duty, nor Justice; and who call, all those your Enemies, that oppose your Pleasures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>Since <hi>I</hi> fight against you without knowing you; you ought not to be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased with me for it: but is it possible, Madam, it should be you that <hi>I</hi> always see at the head of so many false Maxims, which oppose themselves to my designs? Really <hi>I</hi> might easily be deceiv'd in it: after having heard that you were the finest and the most Judicious Person in the World, <hi>I</hi> should never have known you under the appearance of an old quarrelsome Woman, who is always out of humour; who Preaches eternally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst pleasure, and who is Natures Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as well as mine. <hi>I</hi> should know you, Madam, if you did put on a Face more gay; If you were of a less severe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; If you did agree better with Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and with me; and if, in fine, you wou'd furnish us sometimes with Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels proper for our designs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:55740:42"/>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>I understand you, my little Minion; to stand upon good terms with you, <hi>I</hi> must be at odds with my self; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>I</hi> must not be what <hi>I</hi> am, if <hi>I</hi> would make a Peace with you. But do not slatter your self, that <hi>I</hi> will be guilty of so mean a thing: 'Tis more just that Love should conform to Reason, than that Reason should condescend to Love; and <hi>I</hi> will have you know, that there's no comparison betwixt one that is Blind like you, and one so clear-sighted as <hi>I;</hi> betwixt a little rash Boy, and one that's Prudent: If <hi>I</hi> seek after you, 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>I</hi> am naturally good, an Enemy to disorders, and careful to set those right who are out of the way. But you are unworthy of my goodness; you are a little Hair-brain'd Boy, not sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the kindness one wou'd do you, nor of the good advice one gives you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>What! You condemn me for my Transports, and you fall into the fault you blame. You load me with reproaches, you are angry, you are transported your self, and Reason is within a little of seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:55740:42"/> unreasonable. <hi>I</hi> perceive, Madam, that <hi>I</hi> must oblige you to retract to day, and to make you own, that my Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies are better than your Prudence. To which end, since you have now made me some Complaints in general, <hi>I</hi> desire you to come to particulars; and you shall see that <hi>I</hi> will satisfie you in every Article, and that Love has his Reasons, which are better than those of Reason her self.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>I begin to have bett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r hopes since <hi>I</hi> see you Inclin'd to satisfie me. 'Tis no little matter to have reduc'd Love to reason the case; tho' his Reasons, should prove very ill ones; 'tis however to have converted him in some measure: for hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto he has been an Enemy to all that was call'd Reason. Let us take the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage then of the humour you are in, Reasonable Love (for at this time you deserve that Name) let us see what par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reasons you will give for every particular complaint <hi>I</hi> have to make to you. <hi>I</hi> am going to begin with one, which <hi>I</hi> believe will be hard for you to answer. Tell me a little, when <hi>I</hi> have
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:55740:43"/> taken possession of the Soul of a Young Person, when <hi>I</hi> have subjected her to the will of a Father, who has command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to love some one, and to look upon him as one that must be her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; Why do you often make use of your Power to make her Love another, contrary to the Obedience which she owes her Parents? Why do you take pleasure in making her find a thousand defects in the Husband that's propos'd to her, and a thousand Perfections in the Lover which you offer her? Why do you chase me from her, when I put her in mind of her Duty? Cannot the Obedience due to Parents which seems reasonable to all Nature beside, pass with you for a Reason? If you were reasonable, as you wou'd be thought, would you not make her Love what a Father Enjoyns her to Love? Would not you side with Duty, and would not you give her the same Counsels that I do? But 'tis enough that I advise her any thing to oblige you to counsel the contrary. You wou'd think you dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured your self, if you had any Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents conformable to Reason.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:55740:43"/>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>Tho' what you complain of does not happen every day, yet I own that I do sometimes occasion it: but in that it happens that 'tis not I, but the Father that wants Reason. If he took care as he ought to consult me before he made such a command, he should not find me excite revolts against his will. If he were reasonable, he wou'd not antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate my Right, or pretend to act my part in the Heart of his Daughter. I am jealous of my Prerogative and of my Power; and when any Body does Incroach upon them, 'tis but just I shou'd make use of them for my Revenge. I know that the Obedience due to Parents is reasonable; but it ceases to be so, when 'tis to the prejudice of my Authority. The Obedience due to me ought to be preferr'd, when a Father's Counsel and mine disagree. Reason must grant the Counsels of a God are to be follow'd before those of a Man. Besides mine being always agreeable to the taste of those I advise; their end is only to plant tranquility in a Soul that follows 'em; and the advices of a Father, which
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:55740:44"/> oppose mine, cause always an intestine War in the heart of those that receive 'em. So that Reason preferring Peace to War, will have my Counsels follow'd, even when they are contrary to a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>There is some appearance of Reason in your excuse; but what can you answer for your malice in making one Person to be belov'd by many rivals. If you were reasonable, you wou'd not wound seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Hearts with the same Dart. You wou'd give but one Lover to each Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>striss; and but one Mistriss to each Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. By this means you would hinder the fatal effects that jealousie produces every day; and you wou'd not be the cause of a thousand Quarrels, and a thousand Murders, which we see happen among Rivals. For you can't deny that you are the Author of those Disorders, since they would not happen, if you wou'd be content to make each Beauty be belov'd by one Lover only.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:55740:44"/>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis not so difficult as you imagine to prove that I am in the right in what you condemn so much. I know very well, that 'tis against common sense to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make that pass for reasonable, which is condemn'd by Reason. But, Madam, I must tell you now, what I should have told you at first, that it is because you are a being which has never been well known: You put on different Faces to different Persons; and yet eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of these Faces will pass for Reason. You give divers counsels according to the Persons you advise: among those that contradict each another in all their actions, every one maintains that Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son counsel'd him his. 'Tis thus, that many Lovers love one Mistriss, because all of 'em finding her Lovely, they say that Reason bids them all Love her; though it does not appear reasonable to those that don't Love her. 'Tis thus, that a Lover follows the dictates of his Reason, when he frees himself from a Rival that's an obstacle to him, in the pursuit of what he Loves. 'Tis thus, in fine, that those Actors of disorders, whom
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:55740:45"/> you blame with so much violence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they have follow'd your Counsels, when they commit Murders: because you advise those, who love to do and undertake all things, to possess what they Love; tho' those that don't Love say, that Reason teaches that what the others do, is altogether unreasonable; and that, as I have told you, because you give dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent advices to the different Persons whom you counsel.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>If there is no solidity, at least there is Wit in the Reosons you have given: but what expedient will you find to justifie your self when you drive Reason from the mind of an Old Man; when you make him renounce Wisdom to love a Young Person when he might be her Grandfather. I pardon you easily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, when you are content to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Young People to your Empire; for they hardly having known mine, I have no great regret to see them willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly submit to yours. But may I not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain when you come to rob me of my faithful Subjects; those who have so long rever'd me; those, in fine, who are
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:55740:45"/> grown gray under my conduct; for 'tis what you do, when you slide into the Heart of an Old Man: when the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments you give him are opposite to those which I inspire. Is it not doing me a cruel outrage, when you turn topsy-turvy a Mind which I had settled with so much care and pains? What chagrin do you think it gives me to see an Old Man perverted by your Counsels, leave me to follow you; become a <hi>Beaux</hi> in his Old days; shave his Beard, wear little Shoes; dress himself in the gayest co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours; become a Slave to the Fashion; read with Spectacles what you call <hi>Billet doux,</hi> and gallant Verses; play the Child by a Young Person; whisper her in the Ear; go to Balls, Plays, and publick Feasts; and do, in fine, all the Fooleries which I can hardly excuse even in Youth. What—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>If I did not interrupt you, I believe you wou'd never cease complaining up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Chapter; tho' if I had nothing to answer but that I made use of the right of reprisal, when I slide into the Heart of an Old Man, I think I shou'd
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:55740:46"/> not want Reason; for tho' I don't com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of it here, you sometimes rob me of my Slaves, as I sometimes rob you of yours. Very often, when I think my self Master of a Young Heart, you know how to take a time when it has some disdain, some coldness, or some distast, and then seizing on the occasion yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> drive me from it with a great deal of sharpness and scorn: So that 'tis not without Reason, that I too sometimes observe the time when an Old Man has most disposition to leave you, and that with the Fire of some bright Eyes I melt his Ice, and warm the blood which was frozen in his Veins. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess 'tis making your own Subjects revolt from you: But don't you use me in the same manner when you excite Young People to Rebel against me. If this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son appear weak to you, I'm sure you can't answer what I am going to add: You complain that I sometimes make Old Men in Love with Young Women; and you pretend that nothing is so far remov'd from Reason; but I say that there is nothing more reasonable, since by the result of what you have said, a Man should be the wiser the Older he
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:55740:46"/> is, he ought to love that which in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is the most Lovely; and who is more reasonably lovely than a young Person. Wou'd an old Man make use of his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, if he shou'd love one of his own age, where there is neither Beauty nor Comliness, where there's no Fire that can heat him, nor no Charms that can please him? And is it not more reasonable him for to love a young person, which, one may say, makes one young again, and whose Humour and Gayety excites one to Joy and Pleasures? For the rest don't think it strange that he observes in his Actions and Dress all the Gallantries of Youth; since as old as he is, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes young, when he becomes amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. Tho' he minds Fashions, tho' he does all that you call fooleries, he does it with Reason; since, being a Lover, he must endeavour to please the young person he loves; and he knows that the way to please Youth, is to live like 'em: shew the same Desires, and the same Inclinations. Wou'd he b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> welcome to his young Mistriss, if he came Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Vanity and Inconstancy of the Age, railing at Balls and other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions, and finding something to say
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:55740:47"/> against all the pleasures of Youth? Wou'd this be a fine way of making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self belov'd? and has not he Reason when he practices the contrary?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>There is always a great deal of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty in your Answers; but what can you say to justifie the Crimes you commit, when you oblige one that's Marri'd, to love another besides her Husband? Why do you snatch her Heart from him, who is the lawful Master of it, to give it to a stranger, who ought to have no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to it? Why do you separate two Persons whom the Laws have joyn'd, to unite Two others, who can't be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without a Crime? Do you think your self more reasonable than the Laws▪</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes Madam, I am more reasonable than those Laws, which do not so much as consult Reason, in those Marriages, which generally are the Works pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Chance, of Ambition, which s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>metimes mix Fire and Water in joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:55740:47"/> two persons, who have no disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to love one another: have they any shadow of Reason? And has not a Woman more, who finds her self sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected in that manner, to give her Heart to a Gallant that loves her, than to a Husband that hates her; to a Gallant well fashion'd both in Body and Mind, who thinks of nothing but how to please her, than to a Husband ill made and humorsome, who is Eternally grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in the House?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>But tell me, since you are reasonable sometimes, Why are not you always so? I'le allow that you are in the right, when you unite two persons; but are you so again when you separate 'em? If <hi>Thyrsis</hi> had reason to love <hi>Phillis,</hi> is he in the right too, when he ceases to love her? Is he in the right, when he leaves <hi>Phillis</hi> for <hi>Calista?</hi> What excuse can you find for his inconstancy; after having brought me to be pleas'd with his Love, How can you make me love his change? Is it reasonable to despise what he did esteem, and so throw down those Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars upon which he has so often s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic'd, to sacrifice upon new ones?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:55740:48"/>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true, that sometimes Lovers are Inconstant, but they are not without reason in their Inconstancy. When an Object seems lovely to them, they have reason to love it; but when the same Object appears to them no longer so, they are in the right too, to give away their Love. <hi>Thyrsis</hi> had reason to love <hi>Phillis,</hi> because he hop'd to be belov'd by her; he had reason to employ for her all the cares, and all the assiduity that a fair Person deserves: but he had reason to leave her, when he saw that his Cares were in vain, and that his Hopes were without any Foundation. Besides, is it not reasonable to leave the less for the more; to abandon <hi>Phillis,</hi> who all charming as she is, is however infinitely inferior to <hi>Calista?</hi> 'Tis thus, that every Lover is reasonable in his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constancy; tho' he had no other reason for ceasing to love an Object, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it ceases to appear lovely to him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>Tho' I am not fully convinc'd of what you have said, I will not however
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:55740:48"/> lose time in answering you, because I have something to ask you that touches me very nearly. How comes it, unjust Love, that you slide often between Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of an unequal condition; and so unequal, that sometimes, by your Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, we have seen Queens in love with Slaves, and Princes in love with Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants? I willingly pardon you, when you unite persons that are equal. Nay more, I approve your Conduct, I authorize it with all my Power. But how wou'd you have me suffer to see, a Woman of Quality prefer to a Gentleman, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish'd both in Mind and Body, some gross Peasant, in whom there appears nothing that's lovely? How can I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to murmur, when Princes or Lords chuse, to the prejudice of many Ladies as considerable for their Beauty, as Birth; a Country Girl or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, who has nothing in her that's fine or agreeable, but in the imagination of that Prince or Lord, your Malice has abus'd? Must not we condemn your ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularities in such occasions? May not we accuse you of overturning your own Principles, since Sympathy which ought to be the principle of all
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:55740:49"/> your Actions, does not meet in such Loves? For in fine, what sympathy can you find between a Princess and a Slave▪ between a Prince and a Servant? Mean while these are the Loves we see many examples of; and that convinces all the World that you are altogether my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>I never do what you accuse me of, I own that sometimes Princes have lov'd Slaves; but it does not follow from thence, that I have joyn'd two Persons so une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual. When I kindle such a Love, I raise the Slave equal to the Princess, or I humble the Princess to the Slave: and to me they seem always equal, tho' they do not appear so to those, that are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of my Power and mysteries I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve that Sympathy always, which you say I renounce, for Simpathy is not as you seem to think it, a conformity of Birth, of Riches, and of Honours: it is rather a conformity of Birth under the same Planet; to be of one temper, and to have the same inclinations. And may not this Conformity be found sometimes between two persons, which the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:55740:49"/> of Riches and Honours have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd unequal. I cou'd explain it to you more clearly, and let you see that this Simpathy is sufficient to make all the World equal. But 'tis a Knowledge that's reserv'd only for me: and my Policy teaches me, that, for the good of my Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, it ought to be unknown to reason. that Simpathy that hinders equality, those secret Knots, those invisible Chains, that fetter Hearts, and tye Souls, are the foundations of all my Strength and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: or rather, 'tis I that take pleasure to appear only in my Effects, and scarcely ever in my Cause. And 'tis that, which renders my Empire very different from yours; for you Command nothing with absolute Authority, since you are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to give a Reason for every thing. But for me, I act as a Soveraign, and only give a reason when I please. And to tell you the truth, 'Tis a Maxim I have established over all my Empire, that they who Reason well, do not Love well; and that they Reason ill, who Love well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:55740:50"/>
                  <speaker>Reason.</speaker>
                  <p>I see plainly by your last words, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Enemy, that my Conversation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be tiresome; you are not us'd to Reason so long: you suffer too much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in such a Discourse; and tho' I have many things still to ask you, I must make an end, since I grow trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome to you; I am also sensible that I lose my labour, and that it is impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for us ever to be reconciled. I hop'd that meeting at <hi>Calista</hi>'s, we might have contracted an Union, that has never been known between us: and that in the presence of so charming a Person, I shou'd have made Love more reasonable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p>Be comforted, Madam, there is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better happened than what you had undertaken. If Reason has not made Love reasonable, I will believe that in the Presence of <hi>Calista,</hi> Love has made Reason amorous.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="letter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:55740:50"/>
               <head>To a Lady he had Entertain'd in the <hi>Park</hi> in a Masque. <hi>LETTER VIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOU told me last Night, my love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Moor,</hi> when we parted, that I should forget you before Morning; but to let you see how great an impression you have made upon my Heart, I do assure you, that even <hi>Morpheus</hi>'s King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom could not protect me from you; for I dreamt of you all Night, saw your lovely Motions, and that bewitching Air which you do every thing with; heard you speak all those pretty things over again, which you said to me, and blusht to see my self out-done by you in Repartees; nay, and had like to have broke my Man's Head for waking me this Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tho' 'twas for business of concern: thus have you won me, bewitching Charmer, altho' I had but halfe an hours conversation with you, and in a Masque:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:55740:51"/> too: and I assure you, if you had no<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> been so Gracious, as to let me know where to write to you, I had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate e're this time: I conjure yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then, even by that Heavenly Beauty▪ which shines through all the Velve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to Honour me with a Line from you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fair Hand this Night, to let me know where I shall see you to Morrow: fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I do assure you, I shall do such pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in the mean time, as shall have power to make atonement for all the Sins which ever were committed by</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Humble Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Man hath Orders, to bring m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> your Billet to the</hi> Park, <hi>where I shall be sitting on that dear Bench I found you at.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="letter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:55740:51"/>
               <head>The Ladies Answer. <hi>LETTER IX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFTER a long dispute with my self, whether I had best go on in this folly, or make an honourable Retreat, I at last perceived that I had not left my self a fair one, I mean, according to those Romantick Rules of Virtue taught us by our secular Mothers; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was resolved to gratifie my humour a little further, altho' at the expence of some few Blushes; and especially when I consider that I shall take such care, as that you shall never know more of me than you did last Night; and that you may perhaps see me hereafter in such a place; where my Complaisance will oblige me to rally the Masks as smartly as any of the Old Fashion'd Company. After all this, assure your self, that I mean no harm, only to have a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:55740:52"/> Chat with you, which I percei<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> you are very good at. I therefore Cha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lenge you to meet me to morrow a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Seven in the Morning, at the sam<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Bench, and with the same Weapon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in lieu of which I shall bring my Tongu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and Mask; the last of which will, hope, defend my Reputation, as muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as the ugly Face under it will do m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chastity,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Adieu.</salute>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="letter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:55740:52"/>
               <head>The Ladies Address to the whole Assembly of Beaux, at <hi>Hippolito</hi>'s Chocolate-house: <hi>LETTER X.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHere should a Distress'd Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel be so likely to find Succour, as from you Young Lords, Knights, and Squires: To all such therefore I address this my Petition in behalf of a poor Lady, to whom Nature has given some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing a larger stock of sence than to most of her Sex; and not being willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal this Talent, she wou'd fain exercise her good Genius: But alas! in this stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid Age in which all sort of Gallantry is as sophisticated, as French Wines, she has found it impracticable; not then having been so fortunate, as to meet with any single Spark, that did not either want will or Capacity to hold up an
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:55740:53"/> agreeable War of Wit; she sends thi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> as her last Effort to the whole Society▪ Hoping that in such a Numerous Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, some one will be Valiant enough to accept this proffer'd Challenge; and in such Cases let them chuse their ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Weapons, and if they think Love a them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> too Threadbare for their Pen, let 'em name any other, and the Assailant wil<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> endeavour to defend her ground as long as possible; and if Vanquish'd, she'l fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge it, and own her se<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> oblig'd to the courteous Victor, who did not think it beneath him to wage a Writing War with a poor Woman.</p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Direct yours for <hi>Flora,</hi> to be left<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Mr. <hi>Hardings</hi> a Booksellers in <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port-street,</hi> and let me know how t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> send to you again.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="letter">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:55740:53"/>
               <head>The Two following Letters were desired to be Printed by a Fair Lady. <hi>To</hi> Acme <hi>before I had seen her.</hi> LETTER XI.</head>
               <p>I Hope, Madam, you'l forgive the Impatience, that <hi>Love</hi> begets, since I have (tho rack'd with the most eager and Violent of Desires) waited so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tedious Minutes and Hours for a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Answer to my Humble Suit (of being admitted to a sight of you, if not to the transporting Happiness of your Conversation) If, at last, I again trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with a Repetition of it.</p>
               <p>Will not the Justice, and tender Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion that should fill that Heavenly Bosom, grant so much to the most Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>common
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:55740:54"/> of Passions? Can all that Beauty all that Immense Power be without Pity and Justice?</p>
               <p>But you say, Madam, you can't take my former Letter for any thing but a meer Banter; believe me, <hi>Divine Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> I wou'd sooner Banter my <hi>Lawyer,</hi> when my Estate depended on my Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or my <hi>Physitian,</hi> when my <hi>Life</hi> lay at stake, than Banter <hi>You,</hi> the Goddess of my <hi>Heart,</hi> in whom a <hi>Happiness</hi> centers of far greater <hi>Import</hi> than Estate or Life: 'Twould be a sort of Sacrilege to trifle with the Divinest of her Sex, and with an impudent Hypocrisie pretend a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to that absent Power, which all that are Present Adore.</p>
               <p>Ah Madam! though Absent, I am too sensible of your Power, to presume to dally with, and abuse it, who, tho I never yet beheld your Face, (except in Imagination, and in Dreams,) feel all the Racks, and Sighing Pangs of a Poor, longing, tortur'd Lover; and if the Uncommonness, and Extravagance of my Passion, bring its <hi>Reality</hi> into Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, I ought, Madam, the more to be Pity'd, being by that means depriv'd of my best Plea, my <hi>Love;</hi> and, Madam,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:55740:54"/> to doubt that is such an affront to the Immensity of <hi>Your Beauty,</hi> that I can't suffer it with Patience, ev'n from you.</p>
               <p>I. am sufficiently, Madam, satisfy'd, that I err'd not in the former direction of my Passion to you, and you will I hope, remove all doubts of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of my being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>For ever</hi> Septimius.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="letter">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:55740:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To</hi> Acme. LETTER XII.</head>
               <p>I Sent the Inclosed yesterday, but the Bearer, by a mistake, brought it back again, and I had sent it again, had I not been inform'd that you were gone abroad. Ah lovely Charmer! Cast off this ungrateful Veil of Cruelty, that sullies all your Glories, for Cruelty is a Monstrous Ingratitude, returning <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain</hi> for <hi>Love;</hi> for Services <hi>Contempt,</hi> and for <hi>Merit, Disgrace.</hi> The mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Fair indeed, affect it as a Virtue; but Charming Maid, 'tis not to be found in that Noble List; for 'tis nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Prudence, Justice, Fortitude</hi> nor <hi>Temperance Fortitude</hi> bears unavoidable Ills with <hi>Courage,</hi> and repells hurtful and unlawful Force or Injury. But <hi>Love</hi> is so far from being an Ill, that it's a <hi>Supream Good▪</hi> it can never therefore be consistent w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th <hi>Prudence,</hi> to reject the <hi>offer'd Blessing,</hi> since <hi>Prudence</hi> regulates our Actions by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rules of Reason. <hi>Justice</hi> gives to every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lov'd</hi> to the <hi>Lover,</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:55740:55"/> crowning the Constant▪ and Deserving. <hi>Temperance</hi> denies not just Pleasures (for they are founded in Nature, and our Right by its <hi>Fundamental Laws</hi>) but an ill Choice and hurtful Excess.</p>
               <p>Thus, Madam, you see this Idol, your Sex Sacrifices so many <hi>Precious, Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning</hi> Minutes to, is not to be found among the Glorious Rank of Virtues, but is of an opposite Nature, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently a black Compound of the most <hi>ungenerous</hi> Vices. <hi>Cruelty</hi> may well be compar'd to Fortune, both being <hi>Blind,</hi> and the <hi>Reverss</hi> of a <hi>Noble Mind;</hi> for whilst <hi>they</hi> neglect the past Plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Merit, <hi>this</hi> rewards it even in Rags. Fly therefore this pernicious Vice, so unworthy your Beauty, so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy your Youth; for it often brings down those Curses of Despair, that blast all the Glories and Pleasures of the <hi>Obdurate Nymphs,</hi> which, kind Heaven defend the dear charming <hi>Acme</hi> from, and make her avert the impending evil consequence of <hi>Cruelty,</hi> by being propitious to my Flame, and sending me one Line or two, which shall be kept like a Fairy Treasure, in the Bosom of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Devoted Slave, <hi>SEPTIMIUS.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="letter">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:55740:56"/>
               <head>To a Friend who was going to Travel. <hi>LETTER XIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HOW comes this Unkind Silence, <hi>Viridomar?</hi> I hop'd your own Friendship, without the addition of my repeated Desires, wou'd not have let you miss one Post without Writing to your Sorrowful Friend; but here are two past, and not a Word from you Do you begin to break off a Corres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence with <hi>Artemisa</hi> before you leave <hi>England?</hi> That looks Ominous, as if you resolved quite to forget her, as well as never to see her more. Your last, I hope, was not intended for a Final Adieu; No, I must hear from you more than once yet e'er you go, and have an Account what your Designs are, and where you intend to Retire, or I shall never forgive you; You ought to give this Proof of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to my Concern and Grief for you, which is more than you can imagine
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:55740:56"/> My Sister tells me I was never so much a Widow as now in my Life; and I think there is a great deal of Reason for it, no Relation whatsoever being so near as a Faithful Friend, and such I esteem <hi>Viridomar</hi> to be. Indeed I know not what to do with my self; alone I dare not be, then I am almost out of my Wits; all Company I hate; if I sit down to Write, and think I shall not have my <hi>Viridomar</hi> to write to, I am ready to Die; Working is my Aversion; Reading it self does not ease me, for I know not whether I read Sense or Nonsense. I am fit for nothing but a Dark Room in <hi>Bedlam,</hi> only there they make too much Noise for me; Darkness and Silence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the only things can please me, where I can Weep my fill; nor have I any Prospect of any thing will bring rest to my Mind, but the worst of Remedies, the only Catholicon on this side the Grave, Time. But how tedious will that Remedy be? And how do I regret the Thoughts, that <hi>Viridomar</hi> and I must Forget each other? No, sure that must never be! No, no,
<q>
                     <l>Time, nor Absence which destroys</l>
                     <l>The Cares of Lovers, and their Joys.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:55740:57"/> Must not, cannot have that Effect upon a well-grounded, Tender Friendship.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>That's a Weak Love, that Absence can deface</l>
                  <l>Friendship's Immutable by Time or Place.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And ours, I hope, will be so. Yet I must <hi>Never</hi> see nor Converse with you more. Oh that Thought is Unsupportable! Is not that Doom Reversable? Sure, <hi>Viridomar,</hi> it is. One of your Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, who I thought Lov'd you, and who I knew you had a Tenderness for, wou'd now be Dearer to me than all my own, with whom I might freely Converse, and Talk of you; and from whom I might have an Account of all Accidents that may befall you, which my unacquaintance with all your Friends will deprive me of, when you are at so great a Distance. What I Write is strangely Confused and Distracted, (but all my Thoughts are so) if I had never Writen to her, sure you wou'd never have coveted a Correspondence with <hi>Artemisa,</hi> but you know the Cause, and must Pity your</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Most Faithful, and Disconsolate Friend,</hi> Artemisa.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="letter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:55740:57"/>
               <head>From the same, upon the same Subject. <hi>LETTER XIV.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHEN I sent away my last Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I had not time for fear of losing the Post, to Answer yours of the 22d. or hardly to Read it, something I did say, but I know not what; for yours put me into a great concern, which I have not yet Recovered; and could you see the Part I bear in your Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, you wou'd not think I cast you off, because of your Misfortunes; No, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we Part you shall confess <hi>Artemisa</hi>'s Heart is of another Temper. It is my Opinion, that where there is the least Cause to imagine ones Friendship is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sir'd or Priz'd, after an Engagement in it, there is hardly any Cause will justifie the Deserting a Friend; but to do it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:55740:58"/> he is Unfortunate is a Crime of the blackest Nature, and would rank me among the worst▪ and most Flagitious of either Sex; if being as Base and Detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble even as Prostitution it self. If I have Sinn'd against your Friendship (which is very dear to me) by Misjudging of you, I heartily Repent of it, and beg your Pardon; my Mind was in very great Disorder, my Friendship grew very Tender, and was sensible of the least cold Blast. I found your Letters quite of another Nature, and diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rent Stile from what they had been; the more of Kindness I express'd, the more Cold and Indifferent were your Returns, without the least Air of Friendship or Kindness, which at first I attributed to the Troubles and Disappointments you had met with; but when I receiv'd yours of the 8th of <hi>July,</hi> wherein you Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion'd whether there were such a thing as Solid Love? Then I no longer doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but I was again Disappointed of what I value above all things, <hi>viz.</hi> a True Friend. For, certainly, Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, (if Real) is a Solid Thing, nor can there be an Union of Souls without the greatest and most Substantial Love;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:55740:58"/> I grant all other Love is but Flashy and soon over, and therefore does not Deserve to be call'd by that Name; but a well plac'd Friendship in Generous Hearts I should think can never Decay; at least I will answer for my self, that nothing shall abate mine, but the loss of yours; while that continues you may rest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, that neither Time, nor any Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident shall alter me, but I will be your Friend, both in spite of Fate, and of your self too, who are so willing to give me a Dismission; therefore, <hi>Viridomar,</hi> henceforth never Judge of my Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship by any thing but your own; let that rise to as high a degree as you will, mine shall keep Pace with it.</p>
               <p>I know not whether You or I have the Truest Notions of Friendship, but I know I should not do by you as you have done by me: were I in any great Affliction, I should not be so Generous to desire you to Leave me, and to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy your self; and bid you be happy in a more Fortunate Friend; No, I should then endeavour to Retain you, for if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing will Sweeten our Troubles, and make them Easie, it must be the Consideration, that one has a Friend to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:55740:59"/> whom we are very Dear, who Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thizes with, and bears a part in all our Griefs; and wou'd, if it lay in his Power Redress them, nor can any one merit the Name of Friend that does not share in all our Joys, and Sorrows, the first are redoubled, and the last very much lessen'd by the Concern one so Dear to us takes in them. It may be you will say, this is Self-Love, but in it I desire nothing more from my Friend than I will (nor can I help it) return, and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure your self I am as heartily sensible of your Troubles, as if they were my own; and wish it lay in my Power to bring yon out of them, you should then find that <hi>Artemisa</hi>'s is not only a Verbal Friendship.</p>
               <p>I hope, <hi>Viridomar,</hi> you can Forgive the Errors of your Friend, you will the sooner do it, if you call to mind how I have been once Treated by an Ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Friend, and will allow something to my Fears of such another Defeat; I have laid my Heart open before you, as to my Confessor, if you find any Erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta's there, use the Authority of a Friend, and Correct 'em, give me Rules of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship both from your self and <hi>Cicero,</hi> and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:55740:59"/> see if I do not Observe and Practice 'em; for I would have mine as Perfect and Compleat as possible; but tho' you Chide me, do not cast me off, and take your leave of me, that goes nearer to me than all the rest; but you shall not be rid of me so, for now till you tell me you do not Value me, nor think me worthy to be your Friend, I will look upon my self as such, and deal with you accordingly. I am in Pain till I am set right in your Thoughts, and therefore have writ this Post, I send it enclos'd to my Sister, who will send it you by the Penny-Post. Yours, which you say you writ last <hi>Thursday,</hi> I have not receiv'd; I suppose it was an Answer to that I writ giving an account of this Place and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, I am sorry I have lost it, but hope you have a Copy. <hi>Viridomar,</hi> what thoughts soever you have of me, still think me your Friend, and then you will think Justly of her, who is</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your True and Faithful Servant</hi> Artemisa.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="character_sketch">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:55740:60"/>
               <head>Picture of <hi>Orontes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ORontes</hi> is a middle siz'd Man, very well proportioned to his Heigth, but very stiff and Affected; his Face is the worst part about him. I cannot compare his Temper better than to the Character of Sir <hi>Courtly,</hi> whose Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal he seems to be. He is exceeding Civil and Well Bred, and would not be guilty of a Solecism in good manners for all the World. He is a pretender to Wit and Poetry, and passes for the first upon many, for which he is Indebted to good Company and a good Memory: And as Intrigue is the Essential part of a <hi>Beaux,</hi> he is a great admirer of it; but only beats the Bush for others. He looks like a Toper, but is none; yet loves Company, but hates Noise and Clamour, for he is the softest Creature in Nature. He understands <hi>French</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to pervert the Sence of an Author,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:55740:60"/> and is seldom, or never without a <hi>French</hi> Book in his Pocket, of which he is a great admirer. In the main, he is a very honest Gentleman, and very much in favour with the fair Sex: for he will sit you a whole Afternoon with Ladies, and talk of nothing but the Newest Fashions, the most becoming Dresses and Colours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Cajoles and Flatters, sets the Ladies in a Flame, then leaves them to the next Pretender, Trudges to the Coffee-house, and sets up for Politicks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="letter">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:55740:61"/>
               <head>A Letter or Apology of the late M. <hi>Du Ryer</hi> of the French Academy, Translator of the Works of <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> and of many other Books, to which Poverty has not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd him to give all the Perfection he was capable of giving them, and would have done otherwise. <hi>LETTER XV.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HOW, do you praise my Translation of <hi>Seneca!</hi> That may pass with others, but you will never catch me at it again. Know, Sir, that I did it in Six Months time, and that it requires Six Years to do it, as it should be. My Translation is one of<note n="*" place="margin">An Ill Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slator.</note>
                  <hi>Vill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>loin</hi>'s. The only
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:55740:61"/> difference between us, is, that he is very well pleas'd with what he does, and can do no better: But for my part I know my Faults and could mend them. Yes, I have the Vanity to believe, that I could be <hi>d'Ablancourt,</hi> or <hi>Vaugelas,</hi> and I am become<note n="*" place="margin">Another Ill French Author.</note>
                  <hi>Marol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</hi> Oh Fortune, Fortune! It is an Effect of thy Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour. Thou hast compell'd me, against my Will, to Sacrifice my Reputation to thee; but thou shalt never force me to make thee a Sacrifice of my Honour; and I will not deceive my Friend. This, Sir, is an Avowal I owe to you, for the kindness you do me sometimes in lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of me Money: I send you the Twenty Pistols you last lent me. My Bookseller came Yesterday to our Village, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d brought me Two hundred Crowns. I gave them immediately to my Spouse, who is overjoy'd, and makes me happy in my Misfortune. She thinks my Translations as Excellent, as you seem to believe them; and as she is an Eye Witness of my Dispatch; She cannot apprehend how a Mortal can be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of performing such Wonders with so much ease, and fancies that there is
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:55740:62"/> something in me that surpasses Human<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Nature. You have heard of poor <hi>B</hi>— he had Marry'd an <hi>English</hi> Gentlewoman, who Cudgel'd him when he did no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Work so much as she thought he should do. But mine is neither an <hi>English</hi> Woman, nor yet a Gentlewoman; she is a very good Housewife, that Love<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me Tenderly, and honours me with an Incredible Respect. She keeps my little Parlour and my Alcove as neat and as bright as two Looking-glasses; She makes my Bed so well, that I am o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> opinion, no Prince lies more at his ease: and above all things, she never fails to provide me an excellent Soup. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine in my turn, how it is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, with so little Pelf, to make so good a Cheer. So that in spight of Fortune, we pass our Life in admiring each other. She admires my Genius for Translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and I admire hers for Huswifery. Mrs. <hi>B.</hi>—came along with my good Friend <hi>C</hi> — to bring me the Two hundred Crowns, which were remaining due to me for my Translation of <hi>Cicero</hi>'s Orations, which I will send you in few days. That subtle Woman was set out to the best advantage, and saluted me
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:55740:62"/> with so good a Grace, that I am sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that a Bookseller's Shop is as good a School, as the Court, to teach young Women the new Method of saluting People, which the Gallantry of our Nation has lately introduc'd in the World. In a word, Mrs. <hi>B.</hi>—has won my Heart; and has offer'd to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance me the Sum of One hundred Pounds upon my <hi>Titus Livius,</hi> which is very forward. My Spouse immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately whisper'd to me, take her at her word, my dear Husband; I believ'd her, and the said Sum was forthwith pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd in beautiful Gold and Silver, to poor <hi>Du Ryer,</hi> who for fear of ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of you, will trouble you no farther, and will endeavour to do better for the future, than he has done hitherto. I can safely promise it you now, finding my self worth, besides what I have paid you, upwards of Four hundred Crowns; who, since I have known my self, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was so Rich; or rather, never less Poor. Farewell, Dear Sir, do not lose this Letter, which I Desire yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to publish for my Justification, at the head, or at the end of the first of my
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:55740:63"/> Books that will be Reprinted. I am as I us'd to be, that is, with great Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Gratitude.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your most Humble Servant, <hi>DU RYER</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="character_sketch">
               <head>Picture of <hi>Alcidamas.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALCIDAMAS</hi> is of a low Stature, but very well made, Brave and Witty, True and constant to his Friend, Sober and Discreet, and a great admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the Fair Sex, a Qualification which is inseparable from that of a Hero▪ his Discourse is solid, and his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation easie. He is very well read in History, and neither wants Memory nor Judgment. He loves Poetry, and writes a Song or Sonnet very p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ettily. He has a great Genius for Dressing, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:55740:63"/> Intrigue, for which he is admir'd and imitated by most Fops in Town, who are not able to reach his other accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishments. <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided his younger Days, and still are the Darlings of his Soul. He has been, and still is famous for Ogling from <hi>Church</hi> to <hi>Playhouse, &amp;c.</hi> He admires the Creator in his Creatures, and is the True Abstract of Modern Gallantry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Almeria</hi> to <hi>Philander.</hi> upon his resolving to leave her to go beyond Sea. <hi>LETTER XVI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CRuel <hi>Philander,</hi> Is it then possible that you are resolv'd at last to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake the unfortunate <hi>Almeria?</hi> Can you, after so many reiterate Protestations, Oaths, and Vows of Eternal Love and Constancy, resolve to leave a wretch, who can no longer live without you? Ah▪ Why did you take so much pains to Charm, and to undo me, since you
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:55740:64"/> were resolv'd to leave me expos'd to all the Racks and Horrors of Absence and Despair? What injury have I ever done you, to make me so miserable? Sure you never lov'd me; and only seduc'd my Heart to triumph over it. An these, oh Heaven! are these the Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties I flatter'd my self with, when my Soul was full of your dear Image, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my Heart could hardly contain its Joy in hopes of being united to you for ever then, then to hear of Parting, Oh! tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dreadful Word, Parting, and for eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> That Fiend that haunts and torments me perpetually: That Word contains Death and Hell in it! Sure there can be no Sin in an innocent Affection; Why then am I punish'd with an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Separation? Oh barbarous <hi>Philander!</hi> Could you not have conceal'd that cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el circumstance of my Affliction from me, for ever, it would have been time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to let me know, that I must neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> see you more after some years had inur'd me to your Absence. But why do I blame you? It is the nature of Mankind: I should curse my selfe, my Fondness, and my easie Nature, which persuaded me to believe what I wish'd. You seem'd
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:55740:64"/> to love me sincerely; I thought my self oblig'd to you for it, and thought I could do no less than to reward you with my Heart. I was proud to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd by a Man of your Sence and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and pitty'd all my Sex. But now my Joys, my fatal Joys, are dash'd with a never, never to see you more. Whither are you going? Why do you fly me? What can induce you to leave the wretch'd <hi>Almeria?</hi> Is it Honour for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces you from me? No, Honour bids you stay to save my Life; Gratitude will not permit you to leave a wretch that languishes for you, and who had rather die a thousand Deaths, than bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think of leaving you. Think on your Oaths, think on my Despair, and remember that my Life depends on your Resolution. Sure you could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think to leave me, and this was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a trial of my Love, but I ought not to have out-liv'd it; if you have the least niceness in you, you ought never to forgive it: It calls my Love in question, and I mortally hate my self for it. I am on the Rack, and nothing but your Presence can ease my Pain. Return then, Oh! Return to my longing Arms.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:55740:65"/> Yet do not, Why should I desire to see the only Author of my Misery? Fly where your Honour calls you, and boast that you left the wretched <hi>Almeria</hi> lost. Imploy that false protesting Tongue to undo more credulous Maids; but let me never hear it more. I will strive to forget you, or if ever I think on you, it shall be only for my wrongs. I'll hourly call to mind your Falshood, Perjuries, and Treachery, and that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may cure me. Oh Heavens! I am but too sensible of the falseness of that Sentiment; No, it is impossible, I do not wish it; I had rather be unhappy in loving you, than to resume my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Indifference. I impute my mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune to the excess of my Passion. I ought to have consider'd that my Pleasures would end sooner than my Love, and that you would never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake your Fortunes for my sake. I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know what I do, or what I am, nor what I desire. Can any one ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine so deplorable a Condition? I love you to Distraction, yet you will leave me. Do, Cruel, go, I shall not long out-live your Hate; for sure you hate me, or else you could never use me thus.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:55740:65"/> But my Death will for ever disturb your Mind. It invades my Heart already, my Senses are all confus'd, and I can only add, that in spight of your Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, as I liv'd, so I die,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="character_sketch">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sylvia</hi>'s Picture.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SYLVIA</hi>'s neither Tall nor Low, She's Fair and Comly, yet not Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, and has the Air of an Hostess. She is not Witty, yet Subt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, and neither Loves, nor is Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ov'd by any of her Sex; but in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pense, She has been lavish of her Heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o and has receiv'd the Addresses of many a Spark. She is Imperious, Proud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Haughty, Ill-natur'd and Surly, and can dissemble exquisitely. She never misses Prayer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, tho' not out of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion. She seems fond of her <hi>Endimion,</hi> even to uneasiness▪ tho She only adores <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Wealth. She has got an absolute
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:55740:66"/> Empire over him, and knows how to use it. He seems to hug his Chain, and to be fond of his Bondage, tho' some are of opinion, that he only acts the part of a prudent Turtle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="letter">
               <head>From a Lady to her Admired, who is in Love with an Old Woman. <hi>LETTER XVII.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Cruel SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>FOR what can I call you, but Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el and Unkind? who neglective of my Love, can hear my Sighs with no resentments. I have often (you know) when in your company, signify'd the esteem I have for you, and by many Letters made known to you, the frailty of my Affection, which I was never guilty of to any but to you; How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it was my first Experiment, and if it proves fatal to me, I shall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:55740:66"/> to endure it, as a thing coherent to my Misfortunes. I write not these, that I would force your Love; all that I propose, is, to remind you of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess of mine; which as you have slight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and think not worthy your accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, yet at least, give leave to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy to complain. There is Liberty in Love, for Womens Tears; and <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid</hi> gives us leave, when he unkindly wounds our Heart, to make our Moan. You had with you, when I saw you last, an aged Woman; who, I am since in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, has the possession of your Heart; at this I wonder'd, and was sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: thinking it pity that those Worlds of Charms, which always in your Eyes I saw, should lose their Lustre in that ruin'd Face, that weather-beaten Age of Time, in whose despairing Years <hi>Cupid</hi> sits melancholy and alone; Oh! If you are not for me design'd, yet may you be joyn'd to some more happy Mate, and not fade your blooming Roses in her wither'd Trunk. Pardon me, Sir, that I can't praise what you admire; Could I doe e'ry thing I ought, you should have been forgotten long since; but 'tis impossible; you are so fast with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:55740:67"/> my Heart, that when I strive to pull you out, I make it bleed; whence to my Sorrow I am forc'd to tell you, that in spight of all your unkindnesses, I cannot blot you out, but with my unhappy Life; in which, as long as I remain, I shall be always,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="letter">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:55740:67"/>
               <head>From a Lady to a Gentleman, who promising her Marriage, Debauch'd her, and then left her, taking a Journey beyond Sea. <hi>LETTER XVIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Cruellest of all your Sex.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Write not now that I'de re-mind you of your forsaken Vows, for sure you need not these as a reproach to your past Crimes, which always will remain in you, as an opprobrious Object to your future Reflections, that you have wrought an unhappy wretch to Ruin; One, who unskill'd in Mankind's Falshood, had this in her Fate, that she was too loving; whence comes the cause of all my Misfortunes: my ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heart unwarily ran out, and lodg'd
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:55740:68"/> it self with you, which, rifl'd of all its Treasure, you have sent home bleeding, and full of Wounds, which your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindness made, and left it nothing but the Experiment. How wretched have you made me; Ah! Could you have return'd me all, how many Sighs and Tears would you have sav'd me? But Oh! 'tis out of Nature's reach, and as I was then forsaken by my good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, I am likewise left by you for ever.</p>
               <p>Yet as you are going, I will not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with my Sorrows, nor any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make known to you, how misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Love has made me. Let my— go, and with him goe all the kind Stars, no matter what becomes of me; of whom you have no farther use, than only to remember, as an Example, how you may ruine more; Go then, and if in all your Travels you meet a wretch so frail, and so unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate as I, think with a relenting Thought of me again, and save the fond Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from the Ruin I am in, who, tho' undone, by you, yet cannot help, Subscribing my self,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours for ever.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="letter">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:55740:68"/>
               <head>From a Lady to Her Husband in the Camp. <hi>LETTER XIX.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <hi>My Dear</hi> Strephon,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received your kind Letter, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn you thanks for the Satisfaction I enjoy'd in reading you were well, in whose Safety alone depends the stock of all my future Joy; And now, all I have to return you is, that my se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f, and your little Son are well also; whom I have taught to speak your Name, which it repeats hourly, as if like me it wanted you at Home; but vain, alass! are all it's Crys, and my Wishes, since Cruel Wars have rob'd us of you, and made the case uncertain whether I shall ever see you more, unless in the beloved Image of your Dear Child; and in his
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:55740:69"/> Face, his Eyes, his every Feature, do I see you Daily, and feed upon the thought when we may meet again: But when I think of Fights and dangerous Battles, my frighted apprehension makes me fear that you are hurt, and oft I wish that I was there, to dress your Wounds. Thus anxious of your For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune I lead my Melancholly Life, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve no Pleasure in your absence, save that part of Joy only, which I have horded, and keep ready for the time when you shall come again. No Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimes, no Recreations are pleasing to me, but rather inducements to my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>easie Mind, to chide our Fate that makes us Live asunder: Think then on my precautious Fears, and hazard not your Dear Life too far; and though you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it not, yet love it for the sake of mine. Oh! How many Sorrows are in that word <hi>Death!</hi> Which should I hear of you, every Letter in that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Word, would open a Wound within my bleeding Heart, to let my Miserable Life out. But cease my Prophetick Fears, my <hi>Strephon</hi> is yet alive, and Heaven protect and keep him so, which sure, it wou'd could it behold him with
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:55740:69"/> my Eyes, or half the tenderness of my Heart, which for ever is always, his as is my Obligation, who am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your most Obedient, and Loving Wife, <hi>A. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XX.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HOW unhappy is the Man that strives with difficulties equal unto mine! Passionate Love prompts me to pursue a Happiness guarded by Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Honour, the Last of which, is only a Vain Notion to deprive us of true Felicity; a word contriv'd to create Desire, and fill us with a Nobler Esteem for what we wish; but why must I be the only Miserable Person that's baffled with what I know to be but an Empty Name? or do you covet a formal Siege, that the Victory may be greater
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:55740:70"/> Can you forget the Charms of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and the Endearments that attend those who truly Love? Do you find a Chilness run through your Veins, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned by a Chimera of Fear? or do you apprehend you know not what? No, (my Dearest) by all that's Just I will be faithfully Secret, act Honorably by you, nay Swear never to Violate my Word. what have I left Unsaid, Unsworn, that may gain your Favour? Is your Heart impregnable to the Addresses of one that really Admires you? Can you deny him that is yours and only yours? Or do you take a pride in seeing me ruined? Who am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your most Affectionate Friend.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="letter">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:55740:70"/>
               <head>LETTER XXI.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MORE Unhappy is that Woman, who knows not what Path to Tread; my Life is yours already, and must my Honour too? Can nothing serve but an entire Conquest, over that which when gain'd, you'l soon despise? the pleasure of every action is in Desire, and a Generous Heart's is above wishing what may make another Miserable. How can I yield, When I know the Moment I Surrender my Virtue I'm undone? It's that now which alone Buoys me up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midst my greatest Afflictions: methinks <hi>I</hi> can look my best Friends in the Face without a Blush, whilst <hi>I</hi> am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnocent; but alas! When <hi>I</hi> am ruin'd, nothing but Shame can attend each look and thought: Your Arguments might prevail with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, whose Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight secure your Constancy: She might yield; but <hi>I</hi> have nothing but Virtue to secure your
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:55740:71"/> Friendship, which as I prize beyond Expression, I must never part with that which would Infallibly occasion the loss of it. I freely own that you have made deep Impressions on my Heart, and that it is Death to me to refuse you any thing; but when I consider that I must lose you if I yield, my Weakness Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishes, and I have courage enough left to say, I cannot, will not, grant your Request, and yet I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Affectionately Yours.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="letter">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:55740:71"/>
               <head>LETTER XXII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Once could command my Hand with such a freedom that I seldom writ in Vain; But alas! What a change do I find, now I am Penning a Letter to your Dear self, my Lines are faint, my Arguments not perswasive, and every thing seems to contradict my Love: Nay, my very Wishes are imperfect, and the moment I press forward, I expect a repulse; a sence of your Honour bids me desist, and an Ardency of Affection reminds me of the Felicity I shall Enjoy in the Arms of my Dearest Creature. Why were you made so infinitely good, except you'd dispence your Favours to those that passionately Admire you? Or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere you only born to make me Mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable? Does my Dearest distrust the continuance of my Passion, or fear a
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:55740:72"/> fading of my Flame? Do you expect that <hi>I</hi> again repeat Vows of Secrecy and Faithfulness? Or have you sworn never to yield to my Desires? If so, Heaven surely will forgive a Perjury so tender, and forget a Crime that produc'd such effects. Indeed, <hi>I</hi> acquiesce to those Noble Expressions your Letter is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd of, and own the worth of each Line; but why should you so strenuously plead against my being made Happy, or use such Solid Reasons to deprive me of Bliss; since on your complyance de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends wholly my Eternal Misery or Felicity,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours,</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="letter">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:55740:72"/>
               <head>LETTER XXIII.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF Words Express the Sentiments of the Mind, and are the only true means to confirm the sincerity of our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, surely then there remains no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to say, for <hi>I</hi> have given you such Reasons against your Love, as would have satisfied any but your self; and <hi>I</hi> should not again write on so nice a Subject, but that the tyes of Friendship, and the obligations <hi>I</hi> lye under to you, will not allow a Silence. <hi>I</hi> fancy your Pretensions are only for a Proof of my Virtue; and that my Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is more Sacred to you, than the Humour of being Immodest can be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant; neitheir do <hi>I</hi> imagine you can forget, that Men always slight what they possess, and despise what is easily gain'd. Methinks <hi>I</hi> foresee my ruin, and can
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:55740:73"/> look through all your Vows of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy, with Protestations of Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; and you'l believe it, if you'l re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how cold you appear, to some you have heretofore passionately Lov'd; and must I expect a better Fate, who less deserve your Affection? No, no, my dearest Friend, <hi>I</hi> must preserve that which you so much Covet, and never part with what cannot be recall'd: If my Life will serve you, pray command it, for I'll continue Virtuous, whilst <hi>I</hi> am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="letter">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:55740:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Urania</hi> to <hi>Theophrastus,</hi> in Vindication of Age and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency. <hi>LETTER XXIV.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOU say I'm Old, yet give me no reason, why you think me so: but you'd say I am young indeed; if you knew what I can do — Yes, I know what I mean, I can—answer an Assignation, or—<hi>&amp;c.</hi> perhaps you'd expect some greater matters in this, than a bare vindication of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny of Age; which at this time a-day, I think there is but a very small occasion for; Since you have so little Faith, as to believe me Old and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, because my Body is deform'd: Nay, to believe it too, when I have the prospect of— letting you see the contrary <hi>in facto.</hi> Don't mistake me,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:55740:74"/> Sir, I don't intend you shall see it, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I wou'd have you imagine so.— that my Deeds are much more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat than my Person: For a green Apricock at best (you know) is but palatable on one side: but a rip'nd Peach never fails of pleasing. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e'r you may be displeas'd at my man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Writing, I am sure you can't dislike the subject. For as there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Women write what they don't think; so I think what I don't write. This, you'll say, is an odd sort of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression; but I will assure you, a true one. So when I have finish'd this abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Brat, I'll disown it, because 'tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an imperfect <hi>Idea</hi> of my Thoughts. For as I must confess, 'tis much against my inclinations to make Cripples, so tis much against my nature to Nurse them —. Yet in my own defence, I will say this is both Lame in Stile and Thought, because you shan't say, I am a Cold, as well as Old</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Admirer.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="letter">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:55740:74"/>
               <head>LETTER XXV.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <hi>My most kind</hi> Pa, Pa.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HEaven knows the rack I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd e'er since I last receiv'd your Blessing, for want of an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of being happy again. And for that wish'd for Moment, I here avow freely to offer up my Soul, and all that's dear, a Sacrifice to thee my only Deity. But like the Damn'd, at present I am Chain'd to Torments, the kind Powers above grant like theirs, they mayn't be lasting. Dearest Angel, I have receiv'd all your Lines, and must confess, Fate is equally unkind, my Love's as great as yours, and consequently my Sufferings are no less; but assure your self, the first opportunity we will be Blest and Happy; therefore I intreat you to be neither Restless nor Hopeless, so long as you are entirely Belov'd,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>By Your Sighing, Wishing, Panting, Kissing, Dear Girl,</hi> Loriana.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>For Sir</hi> Timothy Squeze <hi>in</hi> Park-Prospect <hi>in</hi> Westminster, LONDON.</dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="letter">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:55740:75"/>
               <head>LEETER XXVI.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Still Charming, and ever Dear.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am so unhappy as to disappoint my Self, and you, by not meeting to Morrow, as I sincerely intended, for as soon as I came home, I was unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately surpriz'd in being Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of Town for Three days to <hi>Epsom;</hi> which will seem Three tedious Ages, there being nothing more desir'd by me, than your most admir'd and agreeable Conversation. May I enjoy it innocently; for whatever you may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine by my free Carriage, from my Soul I abhor any thing that in the least savours of Rudeness, or Nicely touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es upon immodesty, and esteem Virtue and Reputation more than Pleasure or Life. The Liberty you took, when I was last with you, was the occasion of my not seeing you since, and I had made a resolution never to come in
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:55740:75"/> company with you more, tho' at the same time I barr'd my self from my greatest Happiness; for I Declare, if you can relish my Conversation in so Virtuous a way, as I offer, I shall wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly embrace every opportunity to be with you, being unfeignedly,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Admirer, And Eternal Adorer</hi> Amatonta.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>For Prince</hi> Prettyman, <hi>at the</hi> Chocolate-house <hi>in</hi> Bridges Street, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent-Garden, <hi>LONDON.</hi>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="letter">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:55740:76"/>
               <head>LETTER XXVII.</head>
               <p>WITH Horror I remember th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> accursed Moment when I fir<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> gave you the occasion to believe that<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> lov'd you, since you have improv'd i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> according to the Greatness of your ow<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> incomparable ill Nature: A return,<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> confess, I cou'd not but expect from<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gratitude inspir'd by your Wit, tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> prides it self in exposing the weakne<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of those, whom it has deluded. Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> indeed is so natural to you, that yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ought not to be blam'd for it: For, yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> can no more avoid it, than you ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your impious Desires of the ruin of ou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Sex; to which you are as directly and impulsively led, as other poisons are to <hi>their</hi> destructive ends. So that to cal<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> you false, were to be injurious to you since you were ever true to your ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:55740:76"/> ruinous purposes▪ Thou barbarous Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erer of my Peace and Fame! What Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se can reach the Merit of thy Crime! But my satisfaction is, that I need not Curse you: For you are a certain Curse to your self; and your daily Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are so many industrious Attempts <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>owards your own eternal Misery: when, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the same time, I am in hopes, and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ithout reason, that my Crime was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xpiated in the very Commission of it; <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nce it carry'd along with it its own pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ishment, in the sacrificing me imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to the insults of your Scorn and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ngratitude; which (doubtless) is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate of Damnation on this side Hell, proportionable to any impiety whatever, except yours.</p>
               <p>How have I lost a real Heaven for a counterfeit one, that you promis'd me! my continual Peace of Mind for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments flattery! O! Had I retain'd any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity for my self; I had shewn no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion to you. Wou'd to God, you had perish'd in an actual despair, e'er I had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uffer'd such exquisite Torment! Fool that I am! What despair do I think on? Thine? Pretence, Painted Anguish; not to be felt, but by the wretched
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:55740:77"/> commiserating Spectators. Hereafter, may'st thou be truly, as thou wou'dst seem, passionately in love with some fair unbelieving Creature; that shall damn thee to a Real Despair; and so, of course, descend to those everlasting Torments that wait the Ungrateful and Faithless. And may'st thou at thy very last moment, continue remorseless, and impenitent of thy Injuries to me; That thy Soul may appear all spotted over with thy Ingratitude and Perjuries, no desire nor room left for Mercy; that I may be reasonably assur'd (for I hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and wish to out-live thee) that thou art like to be as <hi>Eternally</hi> wretched, as I am now; nay, more if possible! O Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance! Grateful and Sweet as success<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ambition to our Sex, Pursue, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue the Monster! And inspire him at last, in utter and inexecrable Perdition, with a just Sense of all my wrongs; that his <hi>then</hi> unfeigned sorrow for 'em, may prove one of his greatest Tortures▪ Then may the loss of me, whom thou hast most offended, aggravate thy less Plagues of Fire, Confusion, and other Scenes of Horror, in the vast instant o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eternity! I know you <hi>Will,</hi> and <hi>I would
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:55740:77"/> have you</hi> Laugh at this; lest you should unhappily prevail against the just and hearty Prayers of—</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER XXVIII.</head>
               <p>WHat pains (my Lord) you have taken to make me suspect you! yet (I vow) the Entertainment was very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting. You acted the Fool and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the Life! so passing like, that it was, nay, and I believe it is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to think you were otherwise, than as you endeavour'd to appear! 'Twas, in short, an elaborate Scene, and you shew'd a great deal of Mastery in it. Besides, it was perform'd without Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Affectation: For, no Man can play anothers Character so well, as he whom it belongs to. And, as it is an Original, it is new; of a different Cast from any I have ever seen on the Stage, or in my Conversation in Town. And all this for my sake, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade that you love me; which I believe as earnestly and stedfastly, as that you love Partridge and Quail,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:55740:78"/> which can gratifie your Appetite, only in their Destruction: or, rather as you love Oisters, which you devour <hi>alive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had Madam <hi>E</hi> — been here; what a deep, affected Melancholy you had put on! A much more dangerous Madeness, and (as the Physicians say) more difficult to be cur'd, than the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, Roaring, and Bellowing Frenzie, that seiz'd you last night. For my part, I'm of Opinion, that the different, Beauties and Tempers of Women, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the same spark with different Humours in Love. With Her, you us'd to be as melancholy as a Cat; with me, you are generally as Mad as a <hi>March</hi> Hare. To me, it is now, <hi>Prithee</hi> Jenny) <hi>tell me roundly,</hi> &amp;c. To her it was, <hi>Like the Damned from the Fire,</hi> &amp;c. You see you don't Dance in a Net. What wou'd you give now for a Copy of the last Damning Letter she sent you? For, I know you have made but a very ill use of what you receiv'd from her, I suppose that's Torn and Burnt, as once you unhappily made her believe your Heart was Torn and Burnt, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spair and Love of her. She may wish it had met with the Fate of her Letter,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:55740:78"/> which-soever it be, long before you had seen her—But—Lord! — I can't but think, How, in less than a Minute after, I was grown weary and angry with my self, for my little Petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy and Gaiety of Humour, you cou'd change your Note, and sigh out in a dismal lamentable Key— <hi>I still must love on, though I dye in despair</hi> &amp;c. Now, this you must know, was the only way to bring me to my pleasant Humour again. O! that I cou'd by any means be positively assur'd, that you do passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately love me! 'Twou'd (undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly) be the greatest satisfaction and obligation that you could do me. For, you can't imagine how fond and pleas'd I am with a whining, despairing, and dying Lover: But still he must continue so, even to the last gasp of his Breath: when he ceases to despair at least, I shall never endure a Thought of him more. And now (My Lord!) Let me see if you dare Love</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="letter">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:55740:79"/>
               <head>A Character of a Coquet. <hi>LETTER XXIX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF <hi>I</hi> were not persuaded that you are not so severe a Critick, but the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality of Friendship may prevail with you, to pass a favourable Censure, where it is not deserv'd, <hi>I</hi> could not with any Face, trouble you with this Trifle, which falls so every way short of Wit or Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; 'tis an Error only of well-meant Obedience, or at most a rash Sally of that Ill Nature, <hi>I</hi> could no longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. But now to my business; My thoughts beat fast, and Increasing Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice sports within my Veins, and by the help of your Unkindness <hi>I</hi> am Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as fast as I can, in that Excellent Talent call'd Railing, and God knows when <hi>I</hi> shall have done with it: Come, now, I'll be as good as my word after this Preamble; A Woman that is Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:55740:79"/> for any Perfection in Dress, Meen, or Person, presently is honoured with the Title of a <hi>Coquet</hi> Lady, or a <hi>Belle Femme;</hi> there are other Extraordinary Qualities to the making her such; let me see, an Affected Carriage, Confident Discourse, and nothing at all to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose; mighty Pretensions to Wit, tho' she never in her Life said any thing to Procure the Reputation of it, and exces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Censoriousness; which is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to be Imputed to Ill Nature, but to her want of knowing what to do; First you must sit still by the hour, to hear her talk with a disagreeable Noise, against all the absent she or you know; then she fancies her self to have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Sense, because she talks much, and ill of every Body: But if it happen, that you have a kindness for my Lady such a one's Daughter, and she knows you have, perhaps (while you are in Company) she'l turn her humour, and praise her Mantua, or say that she is a dear Woman, dresses moderately Pleasing, and has a tolerable good Humour; but wonders she'd be seen with such a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, or that she will be acquainted
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:55740:80"/> with Unhappy, and Undiscreet Mistriss such a one, for it can no ways be to her advantage. The very Gentlemen that are Lewd with her are not at all beholden to her; for she Rails at them, that no body else should like them, or that she might not be suspected of liking them her self; then she'l flear to the Play, and can't sit down for half an Hour after she comes in, for making of Conges, her Acquaintance is so general, and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares in her Visits, she's as unacquainted with them, as a Lawyer will be to a Cause, when there is nothing to be got by it. She continues in pretty good Equipage for some Years, till her Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and that has had as much wearing as her Chamber-Maids Scarf, or an Old Communion Cloath in a Countrey Church. A little time after, she per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives her Gallants abate their Respects, by pretending business, when she has some for them; they sleight her by telling her she's grown the Refuse of the Town, and bring it to an absolute Quarrel, by laying a Disease to her Charge; then she pretends to go off with flying Colours, as having left him, and so grieves, and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:55740:80"/> keeps her Chamber, gives out the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of it, is a dear Friend of hers that's dead; to carry on the humour, she Sighs, and cries ah! she was the best of her Sex; when the Town and she knows, the true reason is, she's Melancholly, dissatisfy'd with her self and the World, and Wishes that and her self were in flames; In greater or more Violent ones she could not, than perhaps she's in her self: and now she's going off the Stage apace; for now she is come full drive to the Jilting in Hackney-Coaches, and in a little time grows a Scandal to all the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reaking Petticoats, that frequent the Chocolate House; and being past Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of pleasing in her own Person, she employs her self in bringing People to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, who want only an opportunity of Undoing one another. Bawds are now company for Women of Quality, and by their Garbs and dependance can't be distinguish'd. You must know, notwithstanding her Nauseous and Libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinous Life, she has some little Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongst those who are so Unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, as not to have heard of her; then in Company she'l let nothing be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:55740:81"/> but the honourable Intrigues of her Younger Days, (tho' she never had any that was so) the many Adorers she has had, with the several effects, (as she would make you believe) of their desperate Passions, and by what Stratagems they us'd to obtain her Ladiships most Reserv'd affections: Oh! She's in her Kingdom when you talk of Love; yet never will allow any Modern Amour, to be brought into Comparison with those of her Days. At last she Marries a Soldier that beats her, first gets all she has (which is but little) and then Runs away and leaves her to the wide World; she Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents of her ill spent Life; makes a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Lamentation to all her Relations, who usually are of the best Quality; she finds nothing from them but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, who scornfully cry, she's an Old Fool, and deserv'd her present unhappy Condition, for Marrying a Young Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and a Soldier to boot: She goes off the Stage with a Reputation as rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as her Person; passes the remaining part of her deplorable Life, in a tatter'd Old Mantua, carrying News about from one acquaintance to another, for a Meals
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:55740:81"/> Meat, or a Glass of Wine.— This is uncorrect as it falls from my Fancy, and <hi>I</hi> wish it were better for your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Alexander <hi>is Acted to Day, being</hi> Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, <hi>by Mr.</hi> Betterton: <hi>If you'l go in disguise I'll meet you there betimes, Pray send me word by twelve a Clock if you will go, where you will sit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="letter">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:55740:82"/>
               <head>A Character of a Country Lady. <hi>LETTER XXX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOU say I've a very ill Opinion of the Squires, a worse than they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, <hi>I</hi> can't; so that what already <hi>I</hi> have said of them is nearer to Praise, than what <hi>I</hi> could; and to their being deceiv'd in their Wives Fortunes, <hi>I</hi> could not suspect it, since the Kind Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb protects them against all such Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs; <hi>I</hi> wish my self in the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of their Estate, but <hi>I</hi> hardly envy any other of their Circumstances. <hi>I</hi> have Experimented none of their Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, (as you say) <hi>I</hi> generally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them at the Expence of anothers Unhappiness, not my own. Since my last, about a Country Esquire, gave you some Diversion, <hi>I</hi> hope this about a Country Lady in Town may be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd with equal Satisfaction: This Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticoat time has brought up abundance;
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:55740:82"/> according to the Antient and Laudable Custom amongst them; they lie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd two or three Days, in which they Mob it about to their acquaintance, (whose unhappy time 'tis to be trac'd) and to the <hi>Exchange</hi> they go, or to <hi>Round Court;</hi> one place to know whether Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modes continue in that vast Height, or whether any alteration is made in them, since they had their last, those being worn out long since, by often washing: In the other, they go from Shop to Shop, and at last pitch upon the most Unfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shionable, Gawdiest, Gayest Silk, which the Second-handed Mercer sells at an Under-rate, for fear her Allowance from her Father, the Broad or New Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney she has pick'd up at Cards, or sav'd through Good Housewifery, will scarce reach to a better Priz'd one; Then she, to undervalue it, and so by consequence to lessen the Price, crys it Old Fashion'd, though a New one would not please her so well; then the Mother halls the Daughters by the Sleeve, as if she would carry them to another Shop; the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low knows they won't go, he tells them there is no fresher Silk in Town; he makes it up in a sort of Mantua Sleeve,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:55740:83"/> crys, did you ever see Colours better Mingled; Lord! How it sets off the Complexion! sure there can't be a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Natur'd Silk; the Mother crys to the Daughter, Do you like it? Does it please you? Yes, Madam, with a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie; Well, says she to the Fellow, pray Cut it off, good Measure pray, and you must bait the Odd Money; they Pack up their things, come to their Lodings, carry it to their Maid, and to the Mistriss of the House, to shew their Pennyworth; they tell it cost more than it did, to have the Reputation of affording it; If any happen to dislike it, as very few do otherwise, they cry they've no fancy, and nothing can please them; they snatch it out of their Fists, and are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry; the Mother to appease them, crys what's matter who likes it, you are to wear it Daughters. In all this Splendor, the first place they appear Ridiculous in is the Church, and by their shuffing and Pushing get a good place in it: I must needs say they are more attentive at the Ceremony, than our Town La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are, because they are more Custom'd to't; they Sing Psalms that you may bear their Untuneable Voices to the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:55740:83"/> end of the Church; they cry up the Man that Preach'd, for a very Learned Man, because they don't un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand him; they Impose upon some Young Fellow of their Acquaintance to carry them to a Play; they face it in the Box, with their Pockets and Hands full of Oranges, which they buy at the best hand out of the House; they pull out their Handkerchiefs that either smell of Ill Soap, or <hi>Lavender</hi> and <hi>Roses,</hi> and spread it over the Box to lean upon, to save their Ruffles or Sleeves: If they spy any Body they know, cry to their Mother, as if they were frighted; (Oh Leminis!) There is Mr. such a one, shall I bow to him: he coming to them looks as silly as they do, and waits to the leading them out. They generally order their Maid with a Magazine of Sweetness to sit under the Box, ty'd up in one of their Course Genting Handkerchiefs, to tell who they are, if any happens to ask. If the Maid happens to be Prettier than the Mistriss, some Gentleman or other talks to her, and she with much Put-on-Coyness, and feign'd Scorn, crys, Lord you have mistook the Woman, I am
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:55740:84"/> none of that Lewd sort; he finds her stink most Holiday-like of Oranges, and thinks her not worth his while, and leaves her. These Ladies, when they are at Home, stand in the Balcony continually, as if they had taken no other part in the House; Comes by some <hi>Covent-Garden Beaux,</hi> a general designer of Ruining Young Women, like's her, and let's her know it, gets her out upon an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse of shewing her the Queen, the Court, or <hi>Bedlam;</hi> Carries her out to some place, Debauches her as easily as he got her out. In a little time she finds her self with Child, trys all the tricks her Acquaintance can furnish her to prevent it, but all in vain; is carry'd down in haste into the Country; 'tis given out the Town does not agree with her, or that they are afraid she'l get the Small Pox. She offer'd to the Person, with the Encouragement of a little Ready Money, or sent to a Corporation Town to Match with some Alderman's Son; and these Misfortunes have happen'd very often to Country Misses. If my humour of Railing continues, and you have Patience enough, I may give you
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:55740:84"/> the Carriage or way of a Town Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet; This is Just as Country Ladies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themselves in Town, found out by my Observation; and Illustrated but a little by my Invention. The length of this I'm afraid will tempt you to fling it by unread, Judging it not worth the loss of so much time, as the reading it will require,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="letter">
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:55740:85"/>
               <head>To her Lover, a moment after his having left her. <hi>LETTER XXXI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Begin to Write to you, as soon as you have left me. Could my Thoughts be taken up with any thing but you, in the moments that succeed those which we have pass'd together? Ah! My Dear! May I believe the Transports I have observ'd in you, as tender, and as sensible as mine. No, no living Creature ever had Transports like to mine, some Months past, and Love, in order to recompence my Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, has made new Pleasures for me. The Impression they have made upon my Sences, is so Lively, that I have not dar'd to shew my self to any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. It would be yet easie to read the Secrets of my Soul, but my Husband is just entring. Gods! It is very cruel
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:55740:85"/> to be oblig'd to see the Object of our Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in the moment we are parted from that we Love. I must recall the Fear and Modesty which you had banish'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>LETTER XXXII.</hi> Two Hours after it.</head>
               <p>THE Conversation I have been forc'd to undergo, is the Thorn of Roses. Good Gods, what can be more cruel, than to be oblig'd to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain a Man in cold Blood, when we are all in a Flame! Being full of you, and of the Remembrance of our pleasures, What could I say to him? I told him in few words, that I had been in-dispos'd all the Afternoon, and fell immediately to Singing; without minding the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction between those Starts of Joy, and what I had just told him. How should it be possible for me to be wise to day, and to think on any thing but you. But you, Dear Charmer, tell me
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:55740:86"/> how are your Thoughts imploy'd this moment. For my part I think on you, in the same Place, where you have sworn an Eternal Constancy to me. Nothing can equal the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of triumphing thus over the Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy of the Jealous. Heaven! what could equal their Rage, if they know our Happiness. Yet in my Opinion, there is still something wanting to our Happiness, since they have not the grief to know how we deceive them. Let us acquaint them with it to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd of them; but no, Let no body enter into the mystery of our Pleasures, besides our selves. Let us use our utmost endeavours, that the World may forget us, as much as I have forgot it. I fancy the Universe contain but you and I, and I do no longer see any thing, but what relates to my Love. Farewel, Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on increases real Pleasures, and I am glad they should appear in all my Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="letter">
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:55740:86"/>
               <head>LETTER XXXIII.</head>
               <p>ARe your Brains turn'd since I saw you last; you then seem'd reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to me, and now I find you the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest and most unjust of Men. Have you forgot the Reasons I have to deny what you desire? Is it possible that you would hazard your Reputation and my Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for a moment's Pleasure? Ah! tho' they have not been capable to banish Love from my Heart, it is not reasonable that the same Love should Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph absolutely over them; and I am so persuaded, that a Mistriss without Honour can have no Charms for a nice Lover, that you shall never prevail with me to do a thing that will abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ruin my Reputation, in going to the place you propose to me. If I could but hazard my Life without my Honour, to see you, I would not scruple it one moment; my Passion is proof
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:55740:87"/> against any thing but Infamy: You will own it your self, if I can be so happy that the Rendezvous of to Morrow may succeed. I tremble for fear of flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my self in vain, with the pleasure of seeing you alone. I expect it with a sensible impatience. Methinks, that since the Conversation we had last to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the <hi>Park,</hi> I have not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd you sensibly enough of my Love; I fancy I had a presentiment of the long Silence, in which I was going to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd. I never spoke to you more Tenderly, nor with more Boldness; for I own it to you, I often want confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence when I see you, I am only fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar as yet with your <hi>Idea, &amp;c.</hi> I say things to you, when I do not see you, which I dare no longer utter when you can hear them. Come then, Dear Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentor, come to inspire more bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in me, and to Triumph over a small remainder of modesty, which deprives you of hearing me say, What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can be inspir'd by a most violent Passion, and which often costs you the Grief of being oblig'd to upbraid me with being more Passionate in my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, than in my Conversation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="letter">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:55740:87"/>
               <head>LETTER XXXIV.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOU have (doubtless) the greatest and justest reason in nature, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage your desire of Revenge; which, so far, as lies in me, I will be sure to promote. You seem to be fully persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that he loves me passionately, and I am really glad of it, for your sake: For, this his fond mistake shall be as much improv'd to his Torment, as I can contrive, or you desire. But I am strangely oblig'd to your Ladyship, For supposing and wishing, that I may be hapyy in the most ungrateful Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, that ever was sent for the disgrace and ruin of so many of our Sex. However, I find your wonted Good
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:55740:88"/> Nature; or (perhaps) Christian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity begins to exert it self on his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. Since you seem not to deny there is a possibility that you shall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after endeavour to wish him happy. I am unwilling (Madam!) to discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage such Religious and Pious inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in you; tho' I am persuaded, that a like injury done to me, wou'd have brought upon his accursed Head, all the real Plagues within my Prayers and Performances, even to his last gasp: But there I wou'd leave him.</p>
               <p>When next you are pleas'd to engage your self in the trouble of an Answer to this; be pleas'd to send me positive and particular Orders, how I shall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in this Affair: For, if you truly Thirst for Revenge, believe me, you shall not want it, since I will sooner sacrifice my self to him, bound in the strong and durable— (What d'ye call 'em?) <hi>Bonds of Matrimony.</hi> This you must needs own, is none of the least Indications of a sincere Zeal for the service of you; if not, of my self: (unhappily) his Vanity (which you will by no means approve of) will be
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:55740:88"/> apt to flatter him, that it was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in some measure for his sake. Strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therefore consult your own most secret Inclinations; call 'em to a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere account, and advise with 'em what Instructions you had best send by the next, to</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="letter">
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:55740:89"/>
               <head>LETTER XXXV.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am still at a loss to think what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn I shall make you for so great an Obligation, as you were lately pleas'd to confer on me: I am sure, to my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, there can be none proportionable to it in my capacity: No, not though I were the most Adorable Creature breathing, and should grant you the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most favour, you cou'd ask of me; sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing, as Heaven be praised that you are not! of t'other most Perfidious and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Sex; so much I prefer the hopes of my Revenge on that Perjur'd Wretch to all other considerations what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, here on Earth: O! He has so Vitiated my Inclinations, that I can rellish no pleasure but what proceeds
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:55740:89"/> from a prospect of Revenge. This Passion is more advanc'd and unhappily, stronger in me than <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver</hi> I ove was, or cou'd be; because it has more Reason to encourage it, and more ill-natur'd Circumstances to back it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at foolish mistak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e had Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s to enfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> you <hi>(Madam)</hi> I find, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>fore I am like to owe the greatest satisfaction that my Soul can rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive from Heaven, whose kind Instrument of this you may be to me: For he loves you most <hi>ruinously,</hi> to himself, I mean, tho' if you should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend to any kindness for him, the ruin would undoubtedly prove your own. However, if by misfortune, he has, or shall hereafter give you any impression of tenderness for him; I doubt not that you are so well arm'd by your own dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and by my miserable Example, as well as by the hard fate of others, that you will defend and secure your self from the danger of any assault or sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize. But if you must <hi>needs</hi> yield to his Vigorous and Fierce Attacks (for such they are indeed) may it be, as I know it will, upon the most honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conditions that you can propose;
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:55740:90"/> and then, though you surrender, you will have an equal Victory; which may you still maintain, and be for ever hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in him! Then (it may be) I shall endeavour to wish him the same happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness with you: But all this is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for he wou'd as certainly prove Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, tho' Married to you, Madam, as ever he was to</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="letter">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:55740:90"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LEETER XXXVI.</hi> Sent to Madam <hi>G.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Madam.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF Love</hi> be the <hi>Sweetest Passion</hi> of the <hi>Mind,</hi> why causes it all these Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulsions of the Heart to us <hi>Lovers;</hi> Why am I on the <hi>Rack</hi> for you, there is not a <hi>Moment</hi> but I think on you and in <hi>Dreams,</hi> I have enjoy'd that long'd for Moment, but striving to grasp that <hi>Sweet Pleasure,</hi> it flew swifter than the Northern Wind; Oh! could I but have had the happiness, that wretched Fate hath deprived me of. How much above a common Mortal should I esteem my self? But you are resolv'd to be lost to me, as you told me when we were last together, and that I must not enjoy one happy Minute again. Oh! fatal cruel Love, Why hast thou depriv'd me of that which is more dear than my Life and Soul, and the Sight of you, which is more to me than either,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:55740:91"/> and why all at once, as if you design'd to make a Bankrupt of me, or throw me into utter Ruine; I have no hopes left but this of your, of reserving one corner of your Heart, that you intend for one that should be absent from you; give me leave to make use of your own Words, tho' they are cruel, Heart-breaking ones, to one that loves you above the World, and all that's in it; I can't compare my self to any thing, except to a condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Criminal, at the place of execution, that dallies with that which must put him out of pain; your unkindness may have done the work in Two days more; Let me hear from you, I expect my Sentence, or send me a Reprieve by a Letter, or I dye,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Martyr.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From</hi> St. James<hi>'s.</hi>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="letter">
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:55740:91"/>
               <head>LETTER XXXVII.</head>
               <p>IT may be you will think I have taken time enough to consider of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest; but I must tell you, all the ground you have gain'd, is, that if I comply, it is purely as the unjust Judge did with the Widow, lest you weary me with your importunity, and which will be too up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conditions, which if you agree to, I will no longer deny you. First, you must promise me, that no Person what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, without exception, shall ever know who <hi>Silvia</hi> is, but that if it be known you have any acquaintance with me, still <hi>Silvia</hi> may remain undiscover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for if you visit me, I will appear without disguise to you, not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing what belongs to Clandestine Assignations, nor having any fear you should hear any thing wherewith to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach me from my past Actions; this being the most Townish one I was ever
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:55740:92"/> guilty of. Another thing I shall peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily stand upon, is, that I must know who you are, of whom, being you tell me I shall have the true account from your self, I will enquire of no one else; yet will not I insist so hard upon it, that you should, (if you have any Reason to the contrary) send it me in Writing, if you engage to let me know it, without deceit, when I see you; for, I must tell you, that tho' I am not suspitious by Nature, yet if I am once deceiv'd, I am lost for ever, nor can I ever be brought to Trust again. If you will Sign to these Articles, in my next you shall know when, and where you shall see <hi>Silvia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ask my Thoughts of a thing, the least known and practised of any thing in the World, <hi>viz.</hi> Platonick Love, or Pure, Tender Friendship; that Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, I suppose, being only given it, when it is between Persons of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Sex; I confess, for a great while, my Ignorance, (while I judge of others by my self) made me think it, as the finest, so the easiest thing in the World, but I have now got more knowledge of Mankind, and have found to my great
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:55740:92"/> vexation, that, that is the most fallacious way of Judging imaginable. Yet still my Thoughts of that sort of Love, (which I know is possible, tho' hardly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable) are the same, nor do I think any other Love merits to be call'd by that Heavenly Name,
<q>
                     <l>Only the Soul, 'cause that can Love again</l>
                     <l>Deserve's a Love, Deserve's a Lover's Pain.</l>
                  </q> And besides, I think Friendship distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishes us from B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates, far more than our boasted Reason does, in which, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Animals out-do the most of Men, and act with far greater Sagacity; But this Pure Divine Love, this Union of Souls, the Beasts are not capable of; especially, if strictly maintained between a Man and a Woman, and exalts us so far above them, that it almost equals us with Angels; the very imagination has transported me above the Clouds, but I must descend to Earth again, and tell you, for all your pretences to it; I fear this Brutal Age will never furnish us, with one example of this Angelical State.</p>
               <p>I am afraid, in my late vindication of my self, I have done some prejudice to your Friend, which I shall be very
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:55740:93"/> sorry for, not designing any such thing, and therefore I beg of you not to take this advantage, to break with him upon my account, he having done you no injury in the World; but when you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on his Faults, at the same time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member (if that will weigh any thing with you) that he was the occasion of your knowing <hi>Silvia,</hi> who you profess to have a value for; and let him be upon his good behaviour, till he offend again, for I cannot endure to be injurious to any Person whatsoever. I have not as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance enough to impose a Name up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you; <hi>Viridomar</hi> is a Name uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and one I Love, tho' I had rather you should please your self. But I must not forget how you are imploy'd, and therefore I will give you no farther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption, but subscribe my Self</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Servant, <hi>SILVIA.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="letter">
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:55740:93"/>
               <head>Of Friendship. <hi>LETTER XXXVIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>'TWas to prevent your losing your Labour, as you did last Night, that I desir'd to know before-hand of your coming; for my stay in Town be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but short, I am more abroad than I use to be.</p>
               <p>As to the other Grievance you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of, 'tis what I know not how to Redress; for the more I think of it, the worse I like it. You would Impose a new sort of Friendship upon me, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand not, and which favours more of the Body than the Mind; I fear your Notions of Friendship are much too gross for me; and by asking too great Liberties, you will teach me to deny all. An entire Confidence I own there must be, or it is no Friendship; but then that
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:55740:94"/> must only relate to the Soul, of which there is no difference of Sex's, and not entrench upon Flesh and Blood, and expose both my self and Friend to a Temptation may be too hard to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; and in this I betray no greater a Distrust of you than my self; and tho' I think I am so well acquainted with my own Temper not to fear much on that side, yet I will not part with my Guard. Besides, were I of a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour to grant such Favours, Prudence would not permit it, till by long Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse I had (if it were possible) found your Temper and mine to be alike. If you leave me to my self I shall be as Free as Decency will allow; but if you persist in these Demands, I shall be very shy, tho' I fear not turning a Friend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Lover, for I am not cut out for a Mistress.</p>
               <p>As to what you have urg'd from Sir <hi>William Davenant</hi>'s Platonic Love, I shall only say, it may do very well in a Play, where the Representation must always out-do the thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>presented: But should any Woman Act in that manner, I know what wou'd quick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y become of her Reputation; and she that slights that
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:55740:94"/> has already Forfeited her Modesty, and has but one step to lose her Innocence, and all that is valuable in Woman-kind.</p>
               <p>In short, if you wou'd be <hi>Amilcar</hi>'s Successor, as you must avoid his Crimes, so you must Practice what was pleasing to me in him; and there was nothing did more Indear him to me than his Compliance in this matter; for to give him his Due, I must acknowledge, that he never gave me cause to Chide him for his desiring any thing I was unwill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to grant; and he has often Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested, that in my most Intimate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verses with him, he never so much as thought I was a Woman. To Morrow I will be at home to receive you, and am if you please</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Friend, <hi>SILVIA.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advert_for_cosmetics">
            <pb facs="tcp:55740:95"/>
            <head>Advertisement.</head>
            <p>THat Famous Powder, called <hi>Arcanum Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> formerly Prepared by the Learned <hi>Riverius,</hi> Physician-Regent to the French King; and approved by most Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of Quality in Christendom, for Preserving and Beautifying the Face, even to Old Age: It Cures Red Faces, Morphew, it prevents, and takes away Superfluous Hair growing on the Face: In short, it adds more Lustre and Beauty than
<pb facs="tcp:55740:95"/> any Powder or Wash known, as many Persons of Quality can Testifie, who daily use it with the greatest Approbation. It is prepared only by <hi>J. H.</hi> Doctor in Physick, in great <hi>Knight-Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-street</hi> near <hi>Doctors-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons-Gate,</hi> a <hi>Blue Ball</hi> being over the Door, where it may be had for <hi>2 s. 6 d.</hi> the Paper with Directions for its Ʋse.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:55740:96"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Samuel Briscoe,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Charles-street,</hi> in <hi>Russel-street, Covent-Garden.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Satyr of <hi>Titus Petronious Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> a Roman Knight: With its Fragmeets, recover'd at <hi>Belgrade.</hi> Made English by Mr. <hi>Burnaby</hi> of the <hi>Middle-Temple,</hi> and another Hand.</p>
            <p>The Lives of the twelve <hi>Caesars</hi> the first Emperors of <hi>Rome.</hi> Written in Latin by <hi>C. Suetonius Tranquilius.</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated into <hi>English</hi> by several Eminent Hands, with the Heads of the Emperors on Copper-Plates.</p>
            <p>Advice to a Young Lord, Written by his Father, under these following Heads, <hi>Viz. Religion, Study,</hi> and <hi>Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise, Travel, Marriage, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>use-keeping, Hospitality,</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> of <hi>Friendship,</hi> of <hi>Pleasure,</hi> and <hi>Idleness,</hi> of <hi>Conversation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Moral Essay, preferring Solitude to Publick Employment, and all its Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, such as Fame, Command, Riches, Pleasures, Conversation: By Sir <hi>George Mackenzie.</hi> Second Edition.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:55740:96"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>